So last time we were talking about generative models.
지난 시간에는 생성 모델에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And we started off with some discussion of generative
그리고 생성 모델과 판별 모델에 대해
versus discriminative models and recall that these were basically
논의하면서, 이 둘은 기본적으로 확률 모델의 다른
both different flavors of probabilistic models,
형태라는 점을 기억하시고, 우리가 무엇을
but it depends on what we're trying to predict,
예측하려 하는지, 무엇을 조건으로 하는지,
what we're conditioning on, and really critically what
그리고 무엇을 정규화하는지가
we're normalizing over.
중요하다고 했습니다.
So we talked about discriminative models
그래서 우리는 데이터
where you're trying to predict the label y conditioned
x를 조건으로 레이블 y를 예측하는
on your data x, generative models where you're trying
판별 모델, 데이터 x에 대한 확률
to just learn a probability distribution over your data x,
분포를 학습하는 생성 모델, 그리고
and conditional generative models where you want
사용자 입력 y나 레이블 y를
to model the data x conditioned on some user input y or label y.
조건으로 데이터 x를 모델링하는 조건부 생성 모델에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And recall that these differ in that
이 모델들은 정규화하는
what you're trying to normalize over because probabilities
대상이 다르다는 점에서 차이가
distributions introduce this normalizing effect where
있는데, 확률 분포는 정규화 효과를 도입해서
different kinds of things need to compete for probability mass
서로 다른 것들이 확률 질량을
due to this normalization constraint of probability
놓고 경쟁해야 한다는
distributions.
제약이 있기 때문입니다.
And last time we also went through this taxonomy
지난 시간에는 생성 모델의
of different categories of generative models
다양한 분류 체계도 살펴봤는데,
because it turns out this area of generative modeling
생성 모델 분야는 오랫동안
has been something people have studied
연구되어 왔고,
for a very long time, come up with a lot
문제 변형을 해결하기
of different categories of methods
위한 여러
to try to solve variants of these problems.
방법들이 개발되어 왔습니다.
So we went through this family tree of generative models
그래서 우리는 생성 모델의 계보를
where last time we talked about these explicit density models
살펴봤고, 지난 시간에는 모델이 x에 대한 어떤 값
where the model outputs some quantity
p를 출력하는 명시적 밀도 모델에 대해 이야기했는데,
p of x, either the exact predicted p of x
여기에는 계산 가능한 밀도 모델에서 정확한
in the case of tractable density models,
p(x)를 출력하는 경우와 근사
or some approximate version of p of x
밀도 모델에서 p(x)의 근사값을
in the case of these approximate density models.
출력하는 경우가 있습니다.
And then in the case of tractable density,
계산 가능한 밀도 모델의
we saw autoregressive as a category of model
경우, 우리는 자기회귀 모델이라는 범주를
and we saw variational autoencoders
보았고, 근사
as an example of something that gives you
밀도를 제공하는 예로는
some approximate density.
변분 오토인코더를 보았습니다.
So recall that autoregressive models, what we did
자기회귀 모델을 기억해 보면,
is we took our image or more generally whatever kind of data
우리는 이미지나 일반적으로 다루는
we're working with and we break it up into a sequence.
데이터를 시퀀스로 나누었습니다.
And then for the case of image data,
이미지 데이터의 경우,
we typically treat this as a sequence of pixel values or even
보통 픽셀 값이나 심지어 서브픽셀 값의
subpixel values.
시퀀스로 처리합니다.
And we usually want these to be discrete.
그리고 이 값들은 보통 이산적이길 원합니다.
So you treat those pixel values as 8-bit integers that can each
그래서 픽셀 값을 0부터 255까지 값을 가질 수 있는
take a value of 0 to 255.
8비트 정수로 취급합니다.
You string this out into a long sequence of integers
이 정수들을 길게 나열한 시퀀스로 만들고,
and then model this using some discrete autoregressive sequence
보통 RNN이나 트랜스포머 같은
model, typically an RNN or a transformer.
이산 자기회귀 시퀀스 모델로 모델링합니다.
Then we also saw the variational autoencoders,
또한 변분 오토인코더도 보았는데,
which were another explicit density model,
이것도 명시적 밀도
but now they compute not the exact density
모델이지만 정확한
but some approximation to the density,
밀도를 계산하지
in particular a lower bound to the density.
않고, 특히 밀도의 하한을 근사합니다.
So to do this, we jointly trained
이를 위해 우리는 데이터 x를 입력받아
some encoder network which is going
잠재 코드 z에 대한 분포를
to input the data x and output a distribution over latent codes z
출력하는 인코더 네트워크와, 잠재 코드 z를 입력받아
and a decoder network, which is going to input a latent code z
예측된 데이터 x를 출력하는 디코더
and output a predicted piece of data x.
네트워크를 공동으로 학습했습니다.
And we were able to jointly train
이 두 네트워크를
these two networks, the encoder and the decoder,
함께 학습하여 우도 함수에 대한
to maximize this variational lower bound
변분 하한을
to our likelihood function.
최대화했습니다.
Recall that maximum likelihood is
최대 우도는 모든 생성
one of the key insights behind all generative modeling
모델링의 핵심 통찰 중
that often our objective function for training generative
하나로, 생성 모델을 학습할 때
models is somehow to maximize the likelihood of the data
우리의 목표 함수는 관찰된 데이터의
that we observe that comes from our true data distribution.
우도를 최대화하는 것이라는 점을 기억하세요.
So today we're going to continue our discussion
오늘은 생성 모델에 대한
of generative models and explore this other half of the family
논의를 이어가면서, 계보의 다른 절반인
tree, these implicit density models.
암묵적 밀도 모델을 탐구할 것입니다.
So in implicit density models we are no longer
암묵적 밀도 모델에서는 더 이상
going to get access to some actual density value p of x,
실제 밀도 값 p(x)를 얻지 못하지만,
but these models will implicitly model the probability
이 모델들은 확률 분포를 암묵적으로
distribution.
모델링합니다.
And even though we can't compute a density value
비록 어떤 데이터 x에 대해 밀도
p of x for any piece of data x, we will be able to sample
값 p(x)를 계산할 수 없지만, 이 모델들이
from the underlying distribution that these models learn.
학습한 분포에서 샘플을 뽑을 수 있습니다.
So we'll be able to draw samples from the learned distribution
즉, 실제 밀도 값을 출력하지 못해도
even if we can't output an actual density value.
학습된 분포에서 샘플을 생성할 수 있습니다.
So the first such model that we'll explore
첫 번째로 살펴볼 모델은
are generative adversarial networks or usually called GANs.
생성적 적대 신경망, 흔히 GAN이라고 부르는 모델입니다.
And it's useful to contrast GANs with variational autoencoders
GAN을 변분 오토인코더와 자기회귀 모델과
and autoregressive models that we've seen so far.
대비해서 보는 것이 유용합니다.
So like we just said, autoregressive models
앞서 말했듯이, 자기회귀
are a likelihood based method.
모델은 우도 기반 방법입니다.
Their training objective is maximum likelihood.
학습 목표는 최대 우도입니다.
So you write down this parameterized function
즉, 데이터 x에
that is your P of x, where x is a piece of data
대한 매개변수화된 함수 P(x)를
and then you maximize this over the data
정의하고, 관찰한 데이터에
that you observe trying to do maximum likelihood.
대해 이를 최대화합니다.
And variational autoencoders follow this similar idea
변분 오토인코더도 비슷한 아이디어를
where we write down this approximation to p of x and then
따르는데, p(x)에 대한 근사값을
maximize that approximation to p of x.
정의하고 이를 최대화합니다.
And now very generative adversarial networks
반면 생성적 적대 신경망은
will do something a little bit different.
조금 다르게 작동합니다.
They will give up on directly modeling that p of x as we just
GAN은 p(x)를 직접 모델링하는
said, but even though they don't explicitly
것을 포기하지만, p(x)를
model the p of x or let us get out those density values,
명시적으로 모델링하거나 밀도 값을
they will give us some way to sample
제공하지 않더라도,
from the underlying distribution that the model is fitting.
모델이 적합한 분포에서 샘플을 뽑을 수 있는 방법을 제공합니다.
So the setup here is that we'll start
여기서 설정은, pdata라는
by having some finite samples of data, Xi,
진짜 데이터 분포에서 추출된
which are assumed to be drawn from some true data distribution
유한한 데이터 샘플 Xi가
pdata.
주어지고,
And our goal is we want to be able to draw samples from pdata
우리의 목표는 pdata에서 샘플을 뽑을 수 있는 것입니다.
and recall pdata is something like the true distribution
pdata는 우주의 진짜 분포와 같다고 생각할
of the universe.
수 있습니다.
This is the distribution that the universe uses to give you
이 분포는 우주가 여러분에게 데이터 샘플을
samples of your data.
제공하는 방식이며,
And this is likely a very complicated distribution.
아마도 매우 복잡한 분포일 것입니다.
It involves physics.
물리학이 관련되어 있습니다.
It involves history.
역사가 관련되어 있습니다.
It involves sociopolitical constraints maybe.
사회정치적 제약도 관련될 수 있습니다.
There's a lot of complication that
우주에서 일어나는 모든
goes into all the stuff happening
일에는 복잡한 요소가
in the universe that gives rise to the data that you see.
많아서 여러분이 보는 데이터가 생겨나는 거죠.
And somehow we want to fit some approximate model
그리고 우리는 어떻게든 그 진짜 데이터 분포에
that tries to match that true data distribution as well
최대한 맞추려고 하는 근사 모델을
as possible and that allows us to draw
맞추고, 그 모델에서
new samples from our fitted distribution that
원래 관찰한 데이터 샘플처럼 보이는
look like the original data samples that we observed.
새로운 샘플을 뽑아낼 수 있기를 원합니다.
So the way that we're going to do
그래서 우리가 할
this is by introducing a latent variable z.
방법은 잠재 변수 z를 도입하는 것입니다.
This looks kind of like the latent variable z
이것은 변분 오토인코더에서
that we saw in variational autoencoders,
본 잠재 변수 z와 비슷한데,
where it's going to give where this latent variable z is going
이 잠재 변수 z가 우리가 직접
to be distributed according to some known prior distribution
쓰고 조절할 어떤 알려진 사전
p of z that we will write down and control ourselves.
분포 p(z)를 따른다는 겁니다.
And usually this is going to be a unit
보통은 단위 가우시안이나
Gaussian or a uniform distribution,
균등 분포가 되는데, 일반적으로는 단위
but typically a unit Gaussian, something very simple
가우시안으로, 우리가 샘플링하는
that we know how to sample from, we
방법과 해석적 특성을
know the analytical properties of.
잘 아는 아주 단순한 분포입니다.
And now the setup is that we're going
이제 설정은 우리
to imagine some data generating process that our network is
네트워크가 모델링할 어떤 데이터 생성 과정을 상상하는
going to model.
것입니다.
So here we're going to imagine that we sample a z according
여기서는 알려진 분포 p에서 z를 샘플링해서 샘플
to our known distribution p of z to get a sample z,
z를 얻고, 그 샘플 z를 생성기
pass that sample z through a generator network, g of z.
네트워크 g에 통과시키는 과정을 상상할 겁니다.
And then that x is going to be a sample from some generator
그럼 그 x는 어떤 생성기 분포 PG에서 나온
distribution PG.
샘플이 될 것입니다.
And as we vary the parameters or the architecture
그리고 생성기 네트워크의
or the training of our generator network,
파라미터나 구조, 학습 방식을 바꾸면,
that is going to induce different kinds of distributions
이 PG 분포에서
that we sample from in this PG distribution.
샘플링하는 분포가 달라지게 됩니다.
So the whole goal in GAN training
그래서 GAN 학습의 전체
is to try to force this PG distribution, which is induced
목표는 생성기 네트워크가 유도하는 이 PG 분포를 강제로
by our generator network.
조정하는 것입니다.
We want that PG distribution to match the true P data
우리는 그 PG 분포가 실제 데이터 분포 P 데이터와
distribution as close as possible.
최대한 가깝게 일치하기를 원합니다.
And because if they match, then we could sample a z,
왜냐하면 두 분포가 일치하면, z를 샘플링해서
pass it through our generator and now we
생성기에 통과시키면, P
have a sample of sampled piece of data that
데이터와 매우 비슷한 샘플
looks a lot like our P data.
데이터를 얻을 수 있기 때문입니다.
So the picture for this is something like the following.
이 과정을 그림으로 나타내면 다음과 같습니다.
And we'll imagine sampling z from our pz
그리고 우리는 pz에서 z를 샘플링하여 구체적인
to get a concrete latent z, pass it through our generator G
잠재 변수 z를 얻고, 이를 생성기 G에 통과시켜 생성된
and that will give us a generated image.
이미지를 얻는다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
So the generator network basically
그래서 생성기 네트워크는
is trained to convert a sample from a known distribution, z,
기본적으로 알려진 분포 z에서 샘플을 받아서 우리의
into a sample of our data distribution.
데이터 분포 샘플로 변환하도록 훈련됩니다.
But now the question is, how can we force these outputs?
그런데 이제 질문은, 어떻게 이 출력값들을 강제로 맞출 수 있을까요?
How can we force the induced generator distribution PG?
어떻게 유도된 생성기 분포 PG를 강제로 맞출 수 있을까요?
How can we force this to match the data distribution pdata?
어떻게 이것을 데이터 분포 pdata와 일치하도록 강제할 수 있을까요?
And the trick in generative adversarial networks
그리고 생성적 적대 신경망의 핵심은
is that we're going to introduce another neural network
이 작업을 수행할 또 다른 신경망을
to do that task for us.
도입한다는 점입니다.
In the previous versions of generative modeling, VAEs
이전의 생성 모델링 방식인 VAE나 자기회귀 모델에서는,
and autoregressive models, we tried
우리가 최소화할 목적
to write down some objective function
함수를 직접 작성하여
that we could minimize that would force our fit distribution
적합한 분포가 데이터 분포와 일치하도록
to match the data distribution.
강제하려고 했습니다.
Here we're going to relinquish that control
여기서는 그 통제를 포기하고,
and basically ask another neural network
기본적으로 다른 신경망에게
to solve that task for us.
그 작업을 맡기게 됩니다.
So in particular, we're going to train another neural network
특히, 우리는 판별기라고 불리는 또
called the discriminator, D. And this discriminator
다른 신경망 D를 훈련시킬 것입니다. 이 판별기는 입력으로 이미지를
is going to be tasked with inputting an image, sometimes
받는데, 때로는 진짜 이미지, 때로는 가짜
a real image, sometimes a fake image.
이미지를 받습니다.
And it's going to classify whether that image was
그리고 그 이미지가 진짜인지 가짜인지
fake or real.
분류하는 역할을 합니다.
And then the idea is that these two networks are going to fight.
그리고 아이디어는 이 두 네트워크가 서로 경쟁한다는 것입니다.
We're going to train the generator
생성기는 판별기를
to try to fool the discriminator,
속이려고 훈련되고,
and we're going to train the discriminator
판별기는 진짜
as a classification model to try to correctly discriminate
데이터와 가짜 데이터를 올바르게
or classify between real data and fake data.
구분하는 분류 모델로 훈련됩니다.
And the intuition is that as these two networks fight, then
이 두 네트워크가 경쟁하면서, 이상적으로 판별기는
ideally the discriminator will get better.
점점 더 좋아질 것입니다.
It will get really good.
판별기는 정말 뛰어나게 될 것입니다.
The discriminator will get really good
판별기는 진짜 데이터와 가짜
at determining features of real data from fake data.
데이터의 특징을 구분하는 데 매우 능숙해질 것입니다.
And once the discriminator gets really good, then
그리고 판별기가 정말 능숙해지면,
in order to fool the discriminator into thinking
생성된 샘플이 진짜로
that the generated samples are classified as real,
분류되도록 속이기 위해 생성기 데이터는
the generator data will need to get closer and closer
진짜 데이터처럼 보이는 샘플을
to producing samples that look like true data.
점점 더 가까이 만들어야 합니다.
So that's the kind of intuition between generative adversarial
이것이 바로 생성적 적대 신경망(GAN)의
networks.
직관입니다.
So a question is does the generator network get feedback
그럼 질문이, 생성기 네트워크가 판별기가
from the discriminator on whether it's
올바르게 분류하는지에
classifying correctly?
대한 피드백을 받나요?
Yes and that's crucial for this whole process working.
네, 그리고 이것이 이 전체 과정이 작동하는 데 매우 중요합니다.
And the type of feedback it gets is gradients.
생성기가 받는 피드백의 종류는 그래디언트입니다.
This whole thing, this composite system
이 전체 시스템, 즉 생성기와
of the generator and the discriminator
판별기의 합성 시스템은 모두
are just neural networks.
신경망입니다.
We know how to compute gradients through those
우리는 이 신경망들을 통해 그래디언트를 계산하는
and those communicate through that generated image.
방법을 알고 있고, 이들은 생성된 이미지를 통해 소통합니다.
So we're going to back propagate from the discriminator all
그래서 판별기에서 생성된 이미지,
the way through the generated image into the generator.
그리고 생성기로 역전파를 할 것입니다.
So that's how the generator is going to learn
이것이 생성기가 판별기로부터
from the discriminator.
학습하는 방법입니다.
And then more concretely we need to write down
그리고 좀 더 구체적으로,
some actual equations, some actual math that we're
이 직관을 구체화하기 위해 실제
going to use to concretize this intuition.
방정식, 수학식을 적어야 합니다.
So in particular, we're going to jointly train
특히, 우리는 생성기
the generator G and the discriminator
G와 판별기 D를 이 미니맥스
D with this minimax game.
게임으로 공동 훈련할 것입니다.
This equation looks maybe a little bit daunting
이 방정식이 조금 복잡해 보일
so we'll walk through each of the terms one by one.
수 있으니 각 항목을 하나씩 살펴보겠습니다.
So here we're going to color code this
여기서는 색깔 코드를
and say that the generator is going to be in blue,
사용해서 생성기는 파란색, 판별기는
the discriminator is going to be in red.
빨간색으로 표시하겠습니다.
And the discriminator is going to be a function that
판별기는 데이터 x를 입력받아
inputs a piece of data x and outputs
그 데이터가 진짜일 확률을
the probability that data is real.
출력하는 함수입니다.
So in particular, D of x equals 0
특히, D(x) = 0이면
means that the discriminator has classified that piece of data
판별기가 데이터 x를 가짜로
x as fake.
분류했다는 뜻입니다.
D of x equals 1 means that the discriminator has classified
D(x) = 1이면 판별기가 그 데이터를 진짜로
Of course, those are the extreme cases.
물론, 그것들은 극단적인 경우입니다.
The discriminator in practice will output some probability
실제로 discriminator는
that gives you a soft version in between those two decisions.
두 결정 사이의 부드러운 버전을 제공하는 확률을 출력합니다.
Now imagine what happens if we fix the generator G.
이제 generator G를 고정한다고 상상해 보세요.
And just imagine this problem from the perspective
그리고 discriminator의 관점에서 이
of the discriminator.
문제를 생각해 보세요.
So then from the perspective of the discriminator
그래서 discriminator의 관점에서
there's two terms here.
여기에는 두 가지 항이 있습니다.
One, this first term says the discriminator wants
첫 번째 항은 discriminator가 실제 데이터에 대해
D of x equals 1 for real data.
D(x) = 1이 되길 원한다는 뜻입니다.
Remember D of x equals 1 means that the discriminator
D(x) = 1은 discriminator가 그것이 실제라고
says that it's real.
말하는 것을 의미합니다.
And this expectation basically says
이 기대값은 기본적으로 실제
we're going to draw data samples x from the true pdata
pdata 분포에서 데이터 샘플 x를 뽑는다는
distribution.
뜻입니다.
We're going to pass those through the discriminator
그 샘플들을 discriminator에
and then take a log because we almost always work in log space
통과시키고 로그를 취하는데, 확률 작업 시 거의 항상 로그
when working with probabilities.
공간에서 작업하기 때문입니다.
And remember log is a monotonic function.
그리고 로그는 단조 함수라는 것을 기억하세요.
So maximizing log of x is the same as maximizing x.
그래서 로그 x를 최대화하는 것은 x를 최대화하는 것과 같습니다.
So in this case, this is saying that we
따라서 이 경우는 실제 데이터에 대해 D(x)의
want to maximize log of D of x for real data, which
로그를 최대화하고 싶다는 뜻이며, 이는 실제
is equivalent to saying D of x equals 1 for real data.
데이터에 대해 D(x) = 1과 같습니다.
Now on the other side this is saying
반면에 다른 쪽은 알려진
that we're going to take an expectation by sampling priors
prior p(z)에 따라
z--
latent z를
sorry, sampling latents z according to our known
샘플링하여 기대값을 취한다는
prior p of z.
뜻입니다.
We're going to take those z's pass them
그 z들을 generator에
through the generator, which should give us a generated data
통과시키면 생성된 데이터 샘플이
sample, and then pass that generated data sample
나오고, 그 샘플을 discriminator에
through the discriminator.
통과시킵니다.
And now the discriminator wants to classify
그리고 이제 discriminator는 이것들을
as these are fake samples.
가짜 샘플로 분류하고 싶어 합니다.
So the discriminator wants to classify these
그래서 discriminator는
as fake so we need to somehow invert
이것들을 가짜로 분류하고 싶기 때문에
that expression on the left.
왼쪽 표현을 어떻게든 반대로 해야 합니다.
So here we want D of x equals 0 to be fake.
여기서 우리는 D(x)가 0일 때 가짜라고 판단하기를 원합니다.
So one way to say that is maximize log of 1
이것을 표현하는 한 가지 방법은 log(1 - D(G(z)))를
minus D of G of z.
최대화하는 것입니다.
So this term on the right says the discriminator wants
오른쪽 항은 판별기가 가짜 데이터에 대해
D of x equals 0 for fake data.
D(x)가 0이 되기를 원한다는 뜻입니다.
And the term on the left says discriminator wants
왼쪽 항은 판별기가 진짜 데이터에 대해
D of x equals 1 for real data.
D(x)가 1이 되기를 원한다는 뜻입니다.
OK, so that's what the discriminator is trying to do.
네, 이것이 판별기가 하려는 일입니다.
The discriminator is trying to correctly just do
판별기는 생성된
this classification task between generated samples
샘플과 실제 데이터 샘플을 올바르게
and real samples from our data set
분류하는
and try to classify them correctly as real or fake.
작업을 수행하려고 합니다.
Now look at this from the perspective of the generator.
이제 생성기의 관점에서 이것을 살펴봅시다.
So imagine fixing the discriminator
판별기를 고정하고
and looking at this setup only from the perspective
생성기의 관점에서만 이 설정을
of a generator with a fixed discriminator.
바라보는 것을 상상해보세요.
Now in this case, this first term
이 경우 첫 번째 항은 생성기와
doesn't depend on the generator at all
전혀 관련이 없습니다. 왜냐하면
because this first term was just about getting the discriminator
첫 번째 항은 판별기가 실제 데이터 샘플을
to correctly classify the real data samples.
올바르게 분류하는 것에 관한 것이기 때문입니다.
So the generator only cares about this term on the right.
그래서 생성기는 오른쪽 항만 신경 씁니다.
And intuitively, we want the generator
직관적으로, 생성기는 판별기를 속여서
to fool the discriminator into thinking
자신의 샘플이 진짜라고
that its samples are real.
생각하게 만들고 싶어합니다.
So that means that the generator wants
즉, 생성기는 가짜 데이터에 대해
D of x equals 1 for fake data.
D(x)가 1이 되기를 원합니다.
So the term is the same.
항은 동일합니다.
We draw a sample z according to p of z,
우리는 z를 p(z)에 따라 샘플링하고,
pass it through the generator to get a generated sample,
생성기를 통과시켜 생성된 샘플을
pass it through the discriminator
얻고, 그 샘플을
to get the discriminator's predicted probability
판별기에 통과시켜 판별기가 예측한 확률을
on that sample.
얻습니다.
And now recall the generator wants D of x equals 1.
그리고 생성기는 D(x)가 1이 되기를 원한다는 점을 기억하세요.
So rather than maximizing this like the discriminator wanted
그래서 판별기가 최대화하려던
to, instead we're going to try to minimize this
것을 생성기는
from the perspective of the generator.
최소화하려고 시도합니다.
And that gives us this minimax game.
그리고 이것이 우리에게 이 미니맥스 게임을 제공합니다.
So in particular, we can abstract away all this math
특히, 우리는 이 모든 수학을
by writing it as some scalar function v
G와 D의 함수인 어떤 스칼라
as a function of G and D. And then
함수 v로 추상화할 수 있습니다. 그 다음에 판별자는 v를
we say that the discriminator wants to maximize v,
최대화하려 하고, 생성자는 v를
the generator wants to minimize v
최소화하려 하며, 이들이
and they're going to fight against each other in that way.
서로 싸우게 된다고 말합니다.
And then to optimize this we're going to basically run
그리고 이것을 최적화하기 위해, 우리는 기본적으로
some gradient descent loop taking alternating steps trying
생성자와 판별자의 파라미터에 대해 번갈아 가며
to minimize and maximize this with respect
이 값을 최소화하고 최대화하는
to the parameters of the generator and discriminator.
그래디언트 하강 루프를 돌릴 것입니다.
So loop while true forever, then update
그래서 무한 루프를 돌면서,
D according to take a gradient descent step, derivative of v
먼저 D를 업데이트하는데, v를 D에 대해
with respect to D and then step plus that gradient
미분한 그래디언트를 따라 한 스텝
because remember, discriminator is trying to maximize this,
올라갑니다. 판별자는 이 값을
so we want to do gradient ascent to try to maximize this term.
최대화하려 하므로, 그래디언트 상승을 하는 거죠.
And then after we make an update on the discriminator weights,
그 다음 판별자 가중치를 업데이트한
then we'll make an update on the generator weights
후에는, 생성자
by taking derivative of that V with respect to the generator
가중치 G에 대해 v를 미분한 그래디언트를
weights G, and now take a gradient descent step on V
따라 한 스텝 내려갑니다. 생성자는
because the generator wants to minimize that objective.
이 목적함수를 최소화하려 하기 때문입니다.
So that's basically our training.
이것이 기본적으로 우리의 훈련 방법입니다.
That's basically the way that we train
이것이 바로 우리가 생성적 적대
generative adversarial networks.
신경망을 훈련하는 방식입니다.
We've got this thing, V, which is
우리는 이 V라는 값을 가지고 있는데, 이것이
the value of our minimax game.
우리의 미니맥스 게임의 값입니다.
And we're going to take alternating gradient ascent
그리고 우리는 이 목적
and gradient descent weights on that objective V alternatingly
V에 대해 번갈아 가며 생성자와 판별자의 가중치를 그래디언트 상승과
update the generator and discriminator.
하강으로 업데이트합니다.
And one thing that's really important
생성적 적대 신경망을
to realize when we're training generative adversarial networks
훈련할 때 정말 중요한 점은, 이
is that this V is not a loss function.
V가 손실 함수가 아니라는 것입니다.
That means there is no-- the absolute value of V basically
즉, V의 절대값은 생성자와 판별자가 이 문제를
does not tell us anything about how well the generator
얼마나 잘 해결하는지, 또는
and discriminator are solving this problem or how well--
우리가 정말로 관심 있는 것은 유도된 PG
or really, the thing we care about
분포가 데이터 분포와
is how well is that induced PG distribution matching the data
얼마나 잘 일치하는지에 대해 아무것도 알려주지
distribution.
않습니다.
And just looking at the value of V
V의 값만 보는
doesn't really tell us anything about that
것으로는 그걸 알 수 없습니다.
because the value of V depends on how
왜냐하면 V의 값은 판별자가 얼마나 좋은지에
good the discriminator is.
달려 있기 때문입니다.
If the discriminator is really bad,
판별자가 매우 나쁘면,
then it's really easy for the generator
생성자가 쉽게 속여서
to fool this and get good numbers
좋은 값을 얻을 수 있고,
or if the discriminator is really good,
판별자가 매우 좋으면 생성자도
then the generator has to be really good.
정말 잘해야 합니다.
So there can be different settings of D and G
따라서 D와 G의 서로 다른 설정들이 동일한
that will lead to the exact same value for V.
V 값을 낼 수 있습니다.
And that means that generative adversarial networks are often
이것이 생성적 적대 신경망이 종종
really hard to train and even hard to tell when they are
훈련하기 어렵고, 훈련이 잘 되고 있는지 판단하기도
doing a good job at training.
어렵다는 의미입니다.
Normally when you train neural networks, you have a loss.
보통 신경망을 훈련할 때는 손실(loss)이 있습니다.
You try to minimize the loss with respect
네트워크의 파라미터에 대해 손실을
to the parameters of your network
최소화하려고 하고, 훈련이
and you want to see that loss go down
진행됨에 따라 손실이 줄어드는
over the course of training, but you
것을 보고 싶어 하죠. 하지만
don't have that with generative adversarial networks.
생성적 적대 신경망(GAN)에서는 그렇지 않습니다.
You have the generator loss.
생성기(generator) 손실이 있고,
You have the discriminator loss.
판별기(discriminator) 손실이 있습니다.
You can try to plot them, but in general, they're
이것들을 그래프로 그려볼 수는 있지만, 일반적으로
pretty meaningless.
별 의미가 없습니다.
So with generative adversarial networks,
그래서 GAN은
they're really hard to train.
훈련하기가 정말 어렵습니다.
I think, one, this objective is fundamentally unstable.
첫째, 이 목적 함수는 근본적으로 불안정합니다.
You're trying to do jointly maximize and minimize
네트워크의 서로 다른 파라미터 집합에
the same quantity with respect to different sets of parameters
대해 같은 값을 동시에 최대화하고
of the network so that's kind of inherently a difficult
최소화하려고 하니, 본질적으로 어려운
optimization problem.
최적화 문제입니다.
And then even worse, you don't have any value
더 나쁜 점은, 좋은 해답으로
to look at to tell whether or not you're making progress
나아가고 있는지 알려줄 수 있는 값을 볼
towards a good solution.
수 없다는 겁니다.
So generative adversarial networks,
그래서 GAN은
they're pretty effective, but they're really hard to train
효과적이긴 하지만 훈련하기도,
and really hard to tune and really hard to make progress on.
튜닝하기도, 진전을 이루기도 정말 어렵습니다.
So that's the main takeaway for generative adversarial networks.
이게 GAN에 대한 주요 요점입니다.
There is one little trick that is kind of useful to think
GAN 훈련 시 생각해볼 만한
about for when training GANs is that just
작은 팁이 하나 있는데, 바로
to imagine the training dynamics of these things.
훈련 역학을 상상해보는 겁니다.
So at the very start, imagine at the very beginning
훈련 초반을 상상해보면,
of training your generators randomly initialize,
생성기와 판별기가 모두 무작위로
your discriminator is randomly initialized.
초기화되어 있습니다.
What's going to happen?
무슨 일이 일어날까요?
Well, at the very start of training then your generator
훈련 초반에 생성기는 완전히
is producing completely random noise.
무작위 노이즈를 생성합니다.
That completely random noise is going
그 무작위 노이즈는 실제
to look very different from real images.
이미지와 매우 다르게 보일 겁니다.
So at the very beginning of training when the generator is
그래서 생성기가 형편없을 때,
terrible, then the discriminator has a very easy problem.
판별기는 아주 쉬운 문제를 갖게 됩니다.
So typically within a couple iterations
보통 몇 번의 반복만에
the discriminator can really immediately
판별기는 실제
pick up between real images and these totally garbage
이미지와 완전 쓰레기 같은 무작위
random fake images that the random generator is giving you.
가짜 이미지를 바로 구분할 수 있습니다.
So that means that at the very start of training
즉, 훈련 초반에 판별기는
the discriminator is quickly going
실제와 가짜를
to learn to classify these real and fake pretty quickly
꽤 높은 확률로 빠르게 분류하는
with pretty high probability.
법을 배웁니다.
So then it's interesting to plot what is D of G of z?
그래서 D(G(z))가 어떻게 변하는지 그래프로 그려보는 게 흥미롭습니다.
Sorry, what is this term as a function of D of G of z
죄송합니다, D(G(z)) 함수의 값이 어떻게 되는지 보는
because that's basically the loss
건데, 이게 생성기
function from the perspective of the generator.
관점에서의 손실 함수입니다.
So then from the perspective of the generator,
그래서 생성기 관점에서
we're at the beginning of training
보면, 훈련 초반은 여기
somewhere all the way over here.
쯤에 위치합니다.
So the discriminator is doing a really good job
판별기는 생성된 샘플을
at treating generated samples as fake, classifying them
가짜로 잘 분류하고 있어서,
as fake at the beginning of training, which means that
판별기 관점에서
from the discriminator's perspective,
최적화하는
it's trying to optimize a loss function that
손실 함수는 이런
looks something like this.
모양입니다.
And if you'll notice something, this loss function
보시면, 이 손실 함수는
is flat or very close to flat at the place
생성기가 파라미터를 최적화하려는 지점에서
where the generator is trying to optimize its parameters.
거의 평평하거나 매우 평평합니다.
So this means that in practice when you use this naive
즉, 실제로 이 단순한 목적 함수를
objective for training GANs, then
사용해 GAN을 훈련하면,
the generator has a really hard time learning
생성기는 훈련 초반에 배우기
at the beginning of training.
정말 어렵다는 뜻입니다.
Oh, good question is how do you assemble the data set?
좋은 질문입니다, 데이터셋은 어떻게 구성하나요?
How do we generate a photo of a unicorn if no unicorn exists?
유니콘이 존재하지 않는데 유니콘 사진을 어떻게 생성하나요?
So this pdata, that's your choice of pdata.
pdata는 여러분이 선택하는 pdata입니다.
So whatever data set you happen to assemble from your training
즉, 훈련 세트에서 어떤 데이터셋을
set, that's choosing what is the pdata
모으느냐가 모델링하려는
that you're trying to model.
pdata를 결정합니다.
So in general, if you want to generate
일반적으로, 전에 본 적
a sample of a thing that looks nothing
없는 전혀 다른 샘플을
like anything that you've ever seen before, you're out of luck.
생성하고 싶다면, 불가능합니다.
It's not going to happen.
그런 일은 일어나지 않습니다.
So the only way that you're generally going to draw samples
그래서 보통 샘플을 생성하려면,
is if you have something in your training data set
훈련 데이터셋에 그와 비슷한
that looks kind of like that.
것이 있어야 합니다.
So all generative models and all neural networks
그래서 모든 생성 모델과 모든 신경망은 실제로
really do generalize a little bit.
어느 정도 일반화합니다.
So then the hope is that maybe you've
그래서 희망하는 것은, 아마도
never seen a photorealistic image of a unicorn wearing
산타 모자를 쓴 유니콘의 포토리얼리스틱
a Santa Claus hat, but you've seen photorealistic images
이미지를 본 적은 없지만, 말의 포토리얼리스틱
of horses, you've seen photorealistic images of Santa
이미지, 산타 모자 이미지,
Claus hats, you've seen drawings of unicorns,
유니콘 그림, 말 그림을
you've seen drawings of horses and somehow you've
본 적이 있어서, 정확히
got enough stuff, even if you've never
생성하고 싶은 속성 조합을
seen the exact composition of attributes
본 적이 없더라도, 충분히
that you want to generate, you've
비슷한 것을 많이 봐서
seen enough stuff that's close enough to it
모델이 일반화하여 새로운
that the model can generalize and give you something new.
것을 만들어낼 수 있다는 겁니다.
And that's always the hope here.
이게 항상 희망하는 바입니다.
What does this look like from the discriminator's perspective?
이걸 판별자의 관점에서 보면 어떨까요?
So then, well, then if I generated
그래서 만약 제가 산타 모자를
this image of a photorealistic unicorn wearing a Santa Claus
쓴 포토리얼리스틱 유니콘
hat, then maybe all the textures are really perfect,
이미지를 생성했다면, 모든 질감,
the lighting is perfect, the shadows are perfect,
조명, 그림자, 잎사귀가
the leaves are perfect, so there's
완벽해서 그 샘플
no real evidence in that sample itself to say
자체만으로는 명백히 틀렸다고 말할 증거가
that this is obviously wrong.
없을 수도 있습니다.
Maybe if the discriminator was really, really smart,
만약 판별자가 정말 똑똑하다면,
then the discriminator could somehow
유니콘이 실제로 존재하지
know that unicorns don't really exist,
않는다는 걸 알고, 완벽한
and having a perfectly photorealistic image of them
포토리얼리스틱 이미지가 나올
isn't likely to happen, but that's a pretty hard semantic
가능성이 낮다는 걸 알 수도 있겠지만, 그건 꽤 어려운
problem to solve.
의미론적 문제입니다.
So in practice, discriminators tend
그래서 실제로 판별자는 그렇게
not to really be that smart.
똑똑하지 않은 경향이 있습니다.
Yeah, good question.
네, 좋은 질문입니다.
The idea is why don't we look at two curves?
왜 두 개의 곡선을 보지 않을까요?
Why don't we look at one curve saying
왜 판별자가 얼마나 좋은지 나타내는
how good the discriminator is?
한 곡선만 보지 않을까요?
Why don't we look at one curve saying
왜 생성자가 얼마나 좋은지 나타내는
Feel free to plot them.
마음껏 그려보세요.
They tend to look really useless.
그런데 보통은 정말 쓸모없어 보입니다.
And there's probably literally hundreds
이 문제를 해결하고 GAN
of research papers of people trying to solve this problem
목적함수를 어떻게 조정할지 연구하는
and figure out how do we tweak the GAN objective?
논문이 수백 편은 있을 겁니다.
How do we not use a log?
로그를 사용하지 않는 방법은?
How do we use a Wasserstein something, Something-something?
Wasserstein 뭔가, 뭐뭐를 사용하는 방법은?
Put all kinds of crazy stuff into this
곡선을 더 해석하기 쉽게 만들기 위해
to make those curves more interpretable.
온갖 복잡한 것들을 여기에 넣습니다.
Hundreds of papers written about it, five years of thousands
수백 편의 논문이 작성되었고, 수천 명의 사람들이 5년
of people's time, I don't think anybody
동안 연구했지만, 좋은 해결책을
came up with a good solution.
찾은 사람은 없다고 생각합니다.
So still, even after hundreds, thousands of papers training
그래서 수백, 수천 편의 논문이 GAN을 학습시킨
GANs, a lot of people still end up
후에도 많은 사람들이 여전히 이 기본적인
using this vanilla formulation, which
방식을 사용하는데,
tends not to give you very interpretable curves even
이렇게 나누어도 해석 가능한
when you split it up that way.
곡선을 얻기 어렵습니다.
The question is what happens to the discriminator early
질문은 훈련 초기에 판별기가 어떻게 되는지가
in training really important?
정말 중요한가 하는 것입니다.
And the answer is no because this
답은 아니오입니다. 왜냐하면 이것은
is unlike any other classification
우리가 이전에 본 어떤 분류 문제와도
problem we've ever seen before because this is
다르기 때문인데, 비정상 분포(non-stationary
a non-stationary distribution.
distribution)이기 때문입니다.
When you train an image classifier on ImageNet or CIFAR
ImageNet이나 CIFAR 같은 데이터셋으로
or something like that, the data set is fixed
이미지 분류기를 학습할 때는 데이터셋이
and the model is just trying to classify
고정되어 있고 모델은 그 정적인
that static data set well.
데이터셋을 잘 분류하려고 합니다.
But in the case of GAN training, the data
하지만 GAN 학습의 경우,
set that it's trying to fit is changing under it
학습 중에 맞추려는 데이터셋이
during the course of training because even
계속 변하기 때문에, 초기에는 생성된
at the beginning of training, maybe the generated images look
이미지가 매우 형편없어서 문제를
really bad, it's easy to solve the problem,
쉽게 해결할 수 있지만, 생성기가
but then the generator gets better.
점점 좋아집니다.
And now the data set that the discriminator
그래서 판별기가 구분하려는
is trying to discriminate changes under it
데이터셋이 학습 과정에서
during the course of training.
계속 변합니다.
So that means that it's a non-stationary problem
즉, 이것은 비정상
and with very complicated learning dynamics.
문제이고 매우 복잡한 학습 역학을 가집니다.
Yeah, good question.
좋은 질문입니다.
Do these get caught in local minima?
이것들이 지역 최솟값에 빠지나요?
Are there way to kick them out of local minima,
지역 최솟값에서 벗어나게 하는 방법이 있나요? 잠시
train for a while, kick them out?
학습하다가 벗어나게 하는 방법 말입니다.
I think again, hundreds of papers, thousands of papers,
다시 말하지만, 수백, 수천 편의 논문과
lots of heuristics, nothing really stuck.
많은 휴리스틱이 있지만, 확실히 정착된 방법은 없습니다.
Correct, so you have to train this end to end.
맞습니다, 그래서 이걸 끝까지 학습시켜야 합니다.
So gradients from the discriminator
그래서 판별기로부터의
always propagate into the generator so in particular
그래디언트가 항상 생성기로 전달되는데, 특히 오른쪽
through this term on the right.
항을 통해서입니다.
So the only way that you're ever getting gradients
즉, 생성기 파라미터에 그래디언트를
onto the generator's parameters is actually
얻는 유일한 방법은 실제로
through the discriminator.
판별기를 통해서입니다.
I mean, unless you have some regularizer in here,
즉, 여기서 어떤 정규화 항이 있지 않는 한,
but there's no auxiliary term that's
생성자에게 무엇을 해야 하는지
telling the generator what to do other than the gradients that
알려주는 보조 항은 없고, 판별기를 통과하는
gets through the discriminator.
그래디언트만 있을 뿐입니다.
And that's again leading to part of the unstable learning
그리고 이것이 다시 불안정한 학습 문제의
problem.
일부로 이어집니다.
Correct, so that pdata distribution,
맞습니다, pdata 분포는
that's going to stay fixed over the course of training.
훈련 과정 내내 고정되어 있습니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
So we said there's this problem that the generator gets
그래서 우리는 생성자가 훈련 과정에서 낮은
low gradients at the course of training.
그래디언트를 받는 문제가 있다고 말했죠.
There's a little hack here where rather
여기에는 작은 트릭이 있는데, 1 빼기 D(G(z))의
than trying to maximize log of 1 minus D of G of z,
로그를 최대화하려고 하기보다는 대신에
you can instead minimize minus log of D of G of z instead.
-log(D(G(z)))를 최소화하는 방법입니다.
You can convince yourself offline that those are roughly
오프라인에서 스스로 확인해보면 이 둘이 대략 동등하다는
equivalent, but the TL;DR is then it gives you a better curve
것을 알 수 있지만, 요약하자면 이 방법이 훈련 초기에 생성자가
for the generator to get better gradients at the start
더 좋은 그래디언트를 받을 수 있도록 더 나은
of training.
곡선을 제공합니다.
So that's really important.
그래서 이것이 정말 중요합니다.
And whenever you're training GANs
그리고 GAN을
from scratch using this log objective,
처음부터 이 로그 목적함수로 훈련할 때,
then this trick to use the modified loss for the generator
생성자에 대해 수정된 손실 함수를 사용하는 이 트릭이
is really important in practice.
실제로 매우 중요합니다.
So that means that there actually
즉, 생성자에
is a one V that you're computing for the generator, a different V
대해 계산하는 V와 판별기에
that you're computing for the discriminator
대해 계산하는 V가
and they aren't quite the same.
실제로 다르다는 뜻입니다.
OK, there's another question of why
좋습니다, 왜 이것이 좋은 목적함수일
might this be a good objective.
수 있는지에 대한 또 다른 질문이 있네요.
And I used to have slides that walked through this proof step
예전에는 이 증명을 단계별로 설명하는 슬라이드가 있었지만,
by step, but I don't think we have time for that today.
오늘은 시간이 없을 것 같아 요약만 드리겠습니다.
So I'll just give you the TL;DR and we can refer you
그리고 오프라인에서 참고할
to something offline to check, but the TL;DR is that this
자료를 알려드릴 수 있습니다만, 요약하자면 이 목적함수가
objective is good because you can write down this optimal
좋은 이유는 최적 판별기를 쓸 수 있기
discriminator.
때문입니다.
So this is a nested optimization problem
이것은 내부에 D에 대한 최대화,
where there's an inner maximization over D,
외부에 G에 대한
an outer minimization over G. So if you do a little bit of math,
최소화가 있는 중첩 최적화 문제입니다. 조금 수학을 하면 이
you can actually solve this in this inner maximization problem
내부 최대화 문제를 풀고 최적
and write down what is the optimal discriminator.
판별기가 무엇인지 쓸 수 있습니다.
This should actually be the-- this
이것이 바로
is the optimal discriminator with respect
특정 생성자
to a particular generator G. And you can just write this down.
G에 대한 최적 판별기입니다. 그리고 이것을 그냥 쓸 수 있죠.
Of course even though you can write it down,
물론 쓸 수는 있지만 pdata에
you can never compute it because it depends on pdata.
의존하기 때문에 실제로 계산할 수는 없습니다.
And you can never compute pdata because if you
pdata 밀도에 접근할 수
had access to the pdata density, you'd be done.
있다면 이미 문제가 해결된 것이니까요.
So you can write this down as an equation on a slide
그래서 슬라이드나 종이에 방정식으로
or on a piece of paper, but you can never compute it.
쓸 수는 있지만, 실제로 계산할 수는 없습니다.
And then once you have this inner objective,
그리고 이 내부 목적을 최대화해서
once you have maximized this inner objective by writing down
최적 판별기를 구한 후에는, 외부
the optimal discriminator, then you
목적이 최소화되는 조건이
can show that the outer objective is minimized if
PG(x)가 pdata와
and only if PG of x is equal to pdata.
같을 때임을 증명할 수 있습니다.
So at least theoretically the optimum state
즉, 이론적으로는 판별기와 생성기의
of both the discriminator and the generator
최적 상태가 PG가
actually occurs uniquely when PG is equal to pdata.
pdata와 같을 때 유일하게 발생합니다.
So that makes us feel good, but there's
이 점이 우리를 안심시키지만, 이
a lot of caveats to that theoretical result.
이론적 결과에는 많은 단서가 있습니다.
The one is that they both assume infinite potential capacity
첫째, G와 D 모두 무한한 표현 능력을 가진다고
for G and D, that those both assume that your generator
가정한다는 점입니다. 즉, 생성기와 판별기가 원칙적으로
and discriminator can in principle represent
어떤 함수든 표현할 수 있다고
any function, which of course, they can't because they
가정하는데, 실제로는 고정된 크기와
are neural networks of a fixed size and capacity.
용량의 신경망이기 때문에 불가능합니다.
This also tells us absolutely nothing about
또한 이 결과는 우리가 이 해에 수렴할
whether or not we will converge to this solution.
수 있을지에 대해서는 전혀 알려주지 않습니다.
So even though there is this optimum point
즉, 이 목적 함수에는
in this objective landscape, this
최적점이 있지만, 유한한 데이터
tells us absolutely nothing about
샘플과 함께 경사
whether we can ever reach there via this gradient descent,
하강 및 상승법으로 그곳에 도달할 수
gradient ascent, especially with a finite number of data samples.
있을지에 대해서는 아무런 보장을 주지 않습니다.
So there's some sort of comforting theoretical result
그래서 GAN에 대한 이론적
that there is some theoretical justification to GANs,
정당성이 어느 정도 있긴
but in practice, this doesn't really
하지만, 실제로는
hold or give us very strong guarantees.
강력한 보장을 제공하지 않습니다.
So these GANs in practice, your generator G
실제로 GAN에서 생성기 G와
and your discriminator D, both are
판별기 D는 모두
going to be parametrized as neural networks.
신경망으로 매개변수화됩니다.
And they used to be CNNs.
예전에는 CNN이었죠.
The GANs kind of fell out of favor
GAN은 VIT가 인기를 얻기
before VITs became popular, but I'm
전에 인기가 떨어졌지만,
sure they would work with VITs as well.
VIT와도 잘 작동할 것이라 생각합니다.
And the first GAN that really gave non-trivial results
그리고 처음으로 의미 있는 결과를 낸
was called DC-GAN that had this five layer ConvNet
GAN은 DC-GAN이라고 불리며, 5층
architecture, which gave what were at the time
ConvNet 아키텍처를 사용해 당시 꽤
pretty exciting samples.
흥미로운 샘플을 만들었습니다.
And I mentioned DC-GAN because the first author, Alec Radford
DC-GAN을 언급한 이유는 첫 번째 저자인 Alec Radford
et al, for most people doing DC-GAN would have been
등 때문인데, 대부분의 사람들에게 DC-GAN은
a highlight of their career, but for Alec Radford,
경력의 하이라이트였겠지만, Alec
it wasn't nearly enough for him because the next project
Radford에게는 충분하지 않았습니다. 왜냐하면
he worked on right after DC-GAN, does anybody know?
DC-GAN 바로 다음에 그가 작업한 프로젝트가 무엇인지 아는 사람이 있나요?
GPT.
GPT입니다.
So Alec Radford, DC-GAN was kind of a low light in his career.
그래서 Alec Radford는 DC-GAN이 그의 경력에서 다소 저조한 시기였다고 할 수 있습니다.
He went on to do GPT-1 and GPT-2, as well
그는 이후에 GPT-1과 GPT-2를 개발했고, OpenAI에서 다른
as some other amazing work at OpenAI.
놀라운 연구들도 수행했습니다.
So I think there's this really cool connection between people
그래서 이미지 생성 모델링을 하던
that were working on generative modeling of images
사람들이 실제로는 이산 텍스트 데이터의
actually jumped over to do generative modeling
생성 모델링으로
of discrete text data, and did some of the really
넘어가서 중요한 연구를 했다는
important work there.
멋진 연결고리가 있다고 생각합니다.
And one of the only other GAN paper
그리고 제가 강조할 유일한 다른 GAN 논문
that I'm going to highlight is called StyleGAN.
중 하나는 StyleGAN입니다.
I'm not really going to walk you through the details of this one,
이 논문의 세부 내용을 자세히 설명하지는
other than to point you at it as a good one
않겠지만, GAN의 최선의 실천법을
to read if you want to know the best practices of GANs.
알고 싶다면 읽어볼 만한 좋은 논문임을 알려드립니다.
They use a much more complicated architecture,
이들은 훨씬 더 복잡한 아키텍처를
but they get pretty good results in practice.
사용하지만, 실제로 꽤 좋은 결과를 얻습니다.
And one really nice thing about GANs
그리고 GAN의 정말 좋은 점 중
is that they actually tend to learn something smooth
하나는 잠재 공간에서 실제로 부드러운 것을 학습하는
in the latent space.
경향이 있다는 겁니다.
So what I mean by that is that if we have two latent vectors Z0
제가 말하는 것은, 만약 두 개의 잠재 벡터 Z0와
and Z1 and we interpolate between them,
Z1이 있고 그 사이를 보간한다면, 즉
that is draw a sample Z0 from your Gaussian,
가우시안에서 샘플 Z0를 뽑고, 또 가우시안에서
you draw a sample Z1 from your Gaussian.
샘플 Z1을 뽑는다는 뜻입니다.
Then you interpolate some kind of curve between Z0 and Z1.
그다음 Z0와 Z1 사이의 어떤 곡선을 보간합니다.
Then for every point along the curve
그 곡선상의 모든
we're going to generate a sample using our generator.
점마다 생성기를 사용해 샘플을 생성합니다.
Then if we do that, we tend to get smooth interpolations
그렇게 하면 잠재 공간을 통해 부드러운 보간이
through this latent space, which is something
이루어지는 경향이 있는데, 이것이
really cool with GANs.
GAN의 정말 멋진 점입니다.
And here's an example of this latent space interpolation
여기 StyleGAN3 논문에서 나온 잠재
from the StyleGAN3 paper.
공간 보간의 예가 있습니다.
So you can see that these are all generated samples
이 잠재 z를 부드럽게 변화시키고
by smoothly varying that latent z
생성기에 통과시켜 다양한 샘플을
and then passing it through the generator
생성한 것임을
to generate these different samples.
볼 수 있습니다.
And you can see that these animals smoothly
그리고 이 동물들이 서로 부드럽게 변형되는 모습을
morph into each other.
확인할 수 있습니다.
So that means that the model has somehow
즉, 모델이 어떤 식으로든
uncovered some useful structure and stuffed it
유용한 구조를 발견해서
into the latent space.
잠재 공간에 담아냈다는 의미입니다.
So that's pretty cool.
그거 참 멋지죠.
So I used to talk a lot more about generative adversarial
예전에는 생성적 적대 신경망(GAN)에 대해 훨씬 더
networks.
많이 이야기하곤 했습니다.
The pros is basically they have a really fairly
장점은 기본적으로 매우 간단한 수식으로
simple formulation.
표현할 수 있다는 겁니다.
And if you tune them right, like we saw with StyleGAN3
그리고 StyleGAN3에서 봤듯이 잘 조정하면
then they can actually give you very nice results,
정말 멋진 결과, 아주 아름다운
very beautiful images, very high resolution, very good stuff.
이미지, 고해상도, 아주 좋은 결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
But the cons like one like we talked about, they're
하지만 단점은 우리가 이야기한 것처럼 훈련이 꽤
fairly unstable to train.
불안정하다는 점입니다.
You have no loss curve to look at.
볼 수 있는 손실 곡선이 없어요.
You have very unstable training.
훈련이 매우 불안정합니다.
They tend to blow up at the drop of a hat
갑자기 폭발해서 모드 붕괴(mode
so you end up with what's called mode collapse.
collapse)가 발생하곤 합니다.
All of a sudden you might get NaNs.
갑자기 NaN이 나오기도 하고,
You might get infs.
무한대 값이 나오기도 합니다.
Your discriminator starts going crazy.
판별기가 미쳐버리고,
Your generator starts producing complete random garbage
생성기는 계속 완전히 무작위인 쓰레기 같은
all the time.
결과물을 만들어내죠.
You have no loss curves to look at to diagnose this.
이걸 진단할 수 있는 손실 곡선도 없고,
They're kind of a mess.
정말 엉망인 상태입니다.
So even though that GANs can give you
그래서 GAN이 아주
really nice results if you very, very carefully tune them
조심스럽게 조정하고 정규화, 샘플링 등 모든
and very, very carefully control the normalization, the sampling,
것을 철저히 통제하면 정말 좋은 결과를
everything about them, in practice
낼 수 있지만, 실제로는 매우 큰
they've been fairly hard to scale up to really big models,
모델이나 대규모 데이터에 확장하기가
to really big data.
꽤 어려웠습니다.
So GANs were basically the go to category
그래서 GAN은 기본적으로
of generative models from around 2016 to maybe around 2020, 2021,
2016년부터 2020년, 2021년쯤까지 대표적인 생성 모델
something around there.
카테고리였습니다.
And in that five years, there were literally thousands
그 5년 동안 수천, 수만 편의 논문이
and thousands of papers, people both trying
나왔는데, 사람들은 다양한 GAN
to use different GAN formulations, different loss
공식, 다양한 손실 함수, 다양한
functions, different mathematical formalisms,
수학적 형식들을 시도했고, GAN을
as well as applying GANs to all kinds of different generative
상상할 수 있는 모든 종류의 생성
modeling tasks that you can imagine.
모델링 작업에 적용했습니다.
So this was basically the go to generative modeling framework
그래서 이 기간 동안 GAN은 기본적으로 5~6년간
for about five or six years.
대표적인 생성 모델링 프레임워크였던 거죠.
The question is would we just expect this?
그럼 우리는 이것을 그냥 당연하게 기대해야 할까요?
Shouldn't we just expect these smooth latents to pop out?
이 부드러운 잠재 공간(latents)이 자연스럽게 나올 거라고 기대해야 하지 않을까요?
I think not necessarily because one thing that
저는 꼭 그렇지는 않다고 생각합니다. 왜냐하면 GAN에서
can happen with GANs is the generator might just memorize
일어날 수 있는 한 가지 현상은 생성기가 고정된 수의 데이터
a fixed number of data samples.
샘플만 암기할 수도 있기 때문입니다.
So what if your generator ignores the latent z
만약 생성기가 잠재 변수 z를 무시하고 훈련
and just memorizes 10 samples from the training
데이터에서 10개의 샘플만 암기한다면
data set somehow?
어떻게 될까요?
And then no matter what z you give it,
그리고 어떤 z를 넣어도 항상
it always gives you one of those 10 samples
그 10개의 샘플 중 하나만
from the training data set, and it never
출력하고 다른 것은 전혀 내놓지
gives you anything else.
않는다면 말이죠.
Then in that case, you're going to fool the discriminator
그 경우에는 생성기가 항상 실제 샘플 중
because the generator is always giving you
하나와 비트 단위로 동일한
something which is maybe bit wise identical to one
것을 내놓기 때문에 판별기를 속일
of your real samples.
수 있습니다.
And then in that case, the generator
그렇게 되면 생성기는
would have basically piled on Dirac delta
사실상 몇 개의 유한한 샘플 근처에
density in the immediate vicinity
Dirac 델타 밀도를 쌓아놓고,
of a couple finite samples, but put no probability mass
다른 곳에는 확률 질량을 전혀 두지 않은
anywhere else.
셈이 됩니다.
So that actually is a legitimate solution for the generator.
그래서 그게 생성기에게는 합법적인 해답이 될 수 있습니다.
And that would definitely not give you smooth latents at all.
그리고 그 경우에는 절대 부드러운 잠재 공간을 얻을 수 없습니다.
So that's just one example of how these things can
이것이 바로 이런 모델들이 우리가 원하는
collapse into unintuitive solutions that are not
것과는 다른, 직관적이지 않은 해답으로
what you want.
붕괴할 수 있는 한 예입니다.
Oh, good question.
아, 좋은 질문입니다.
What is the relationship between your training data
훈련 데이터셋과 잠재 변수 사이에는
set and your latents?
어떤 관계가 있을까요?
So this is actually something very fundamental
이것은 GAN에 대해 매우
about GANs is a great question.
근본적인 질문입니다.
So you can map one way.
그래서 한 방향으로 매핑할 수 있습니다.
So the generator gives you a mapping
그래서 생성기는 잠재 공간에서
from latent space into data space, maps from z to an x,
데이터 공간으로 매핑을 제공합니다. z에서 x로 매핑하죠.
but with GANs you in general have no way
하지만 GAN에서는 일반적으로
to map back from an x to a z.
x에서 z로 다시 매핑할 방법이 없습니다.
And that's something very different between GANs and VAEs.
이 점이 GAN과 VAE의 아주 큰 차이점입니다.
So VAEs will learn an explicit mapping from x to z,
VAE는 x에서 z로 명시적인 매핑을 학습하지만,
but with GANs you have no such thing.
GAN에는 그런 것이 없습니다.
You can try to invert-- you can try
역으로 계산하려고 시도할
to compute an inverse numerically
수는 있습니다—경사 하강법으로 수치적으로 역함수를
via gradient descent.
구할 수도 있죠.
And there's papers that do that, but there's actually
그런 논문들도 있지만, 사실 x와
no explicitly enforced relationship between x and z.
z 사이에 명시적으로 강제된 관계는 없습니다.
Instead, you can think of the discriminator
대신 판별기는 생성기에서
as trying to just enforce a distributional alignment
나오는 출력들의 분포와 실제 데이터
between the distribution of all the outputs coming
샘플들의 분포 사이의 분포
from the generator and the distribution of all the data
정렬을 강제하려고 한다고
samples, without any kind of explicit supervision
생각할 수 있습니다. 명시적인
between them.
감독 없이요.
Of course, when it comes to GANs,
물론 GAN에 관해서라면, 아마도
anything you probably think about,
여러분이 생각하는 거의 모든 것에
there's probably at least a dozen papers about.
대해 최소한 열두 편 이상의 논문이 있을 겁니다.
So there's also a lot of papers about GAN variants
양방향 매핑을 모두 학습하려는 GAN
that try to learn bidirectional mappings both ways,
변형에 관한 논문도 많지만, 그런
but those never really took off.
시도들은 크게 성공하지 못했습니다.
Oh, good question.
좋은 질문입니다.
What have we gained?
우리가 얻은 것은 무엇일까요?
So when we went to VAEs we gained latent vectors,
VAE로 넘어가면서 잠재 벡터를 얻었지만, 밀도
but we gave up density.
추정은 포기했습니다.
And now with GANs it seems like we gave up latent vectors
그리고 GAN에서는 우리가 제어할 수 있는 잠재 벡터를
that we can control.
포기한 것처럼 보입니다.
What you gained was much better samples.
하지만 얻은 것은 훨씬 더 좋은 샘플입니다.
So when it comes to VAEs, VAEs tend not
VAE의 경우, VAE는 좋은 샘플을
to give you very good samples.
주지 않는 경향이 있습니다.
VAEs are characteristically always blurry.
VAE는 특징적으로 항상 흐릿합니다.
They never really look good.
그들은 결코 정말 좋아 보이지 않습니다.
VAEs on their own just never tend to give you very clean,
VAEs만으로는 절대 아주 깔끔하고
crisp samples, but with GANs, as you
선명한 샘플을 주지 않지만, GANs를
saw with some of the examples, you
사용하면 몇 가지
can get very crisp, very clean, very good samples,
예에서 보셨듯이 아주 선명하고 깔끔하며 좋은 샘플을 얻을 수 있습니다. 하지만
but what you lost was your sanity
이런 시스템을 조정하려고
in trying to tune these systems.
하면 정신을 잃게 됩니다.
Yeah, at inference time you throw away the discriminator
네, 추론 시에는 discriminator를 버리고
and just use the generator.
generator만 사용합니다.
So at inference you'll just draw a sample z from the prior,
그래서 추론할 때는 prior에서 샘플 z를 뽑아 generator에
pass through the generator, get your sample from your data.
통과시키면 데이터에서 샘플을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So it's very, very efficient at inference time.
그래서 추론 시에는 매우, 매우 효율적입니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
So I mentioned that GANs used to be
GANs가 약 5~6년
the go to category of generative modeling for about five
동안 생성 모델링의 대표적인 범주였다고
or six years.
말씀드렸죠.
So what displaced them?
그럼 무엇이 그들을 대체했을까요?
And what displaced them was a very different category
그것은 diffusion models라는 아주
of models called diffusion models.
다른 범주의 모델이었습니다.
Now I need to put some caveats here.
여기서 몇 가지 주의사항을 말씀드려야 합니다.
Diffusion model literature is crazy.
Diffusion model 관련 문헌은 정말 복잡합니다.
You read these papers, they go through five pages of math
논문을 읽으면 무슨 일이 일어나는지 알려주기
before they tell you at all what's going on.
전에 수학이 5페이지나 나옵니다.
And there's three different mathematical formalisms
그리고 diffusion models로 이어지는 세 가지 서로
that lead to diffusion models that are all
다른 수학적 형식이 있는데, 모두
very different mathematically.
수학적으로 매우 다릅니다.
And there's very different notation, very different
논문마다 표기법, 용어,
terminology, very different mathematical formalisms
수학적 형식이 매우
between papers.
다릅니다.
So this is a subarea that's crazy.
그래서 이 분야는 정말 복잡한 하위 영역입니다.
So I need to put a big caveat here
그래서 모든 diffusion
that I'm not going to cover fully all the different variants
model 변형과 그에 따른 수학적 형식을 완전히
of diffusion models with all of their proper mathematical
다루지 않을 것이라는 점을 크게 주의하셔야
formalism.
합니다.
Instead, what I'm going to try to do
대신에, 제가 하려는 것은
is give you an intuitive overview of diffusion models,
diffusion 모델에 대한 직관적인 개요와
as well as an intuitive geometric understanding
오늘날 가장 흔한 형태인 rectified
of the most common form of diffusion models today,
flow 모델에 대한 직관적인
which are called rectified flow models.
기하학적 이해를 드리는 것입니다.
And you could teach many, many lectures about diffusion models
diffusion 모델에 대해 많은 강의를
and get into all the interesting mathematical nuance of all these
할 수 있고 다양한 수학적 세부사항을
flavors, but we just won't have time for that in 2/3 of one
다룰 수 있지만, 불행히도 한 강의의 2/3
lecture, unfortunately.
시간 안에 그럴 여유는 없습니다.
So with that caveat aside, the intuition
그 점을 감안하고 나면, diffusion
behind diffusion models is actually easy.
모델의 직관은 사실 쉽습니다.
So with all generative models, we want to draw samples.
모든 생성 모델과 마찬가지로, 우리는 샘플을 뽑고 싶습니다.
And like GANs, we want to convert samples from a noise
GAN처럼, 우리는 노이즈 분포 z에서 데이터 분포
distribution z into a data distribution, px,
px로 샘플을 변환하고 싶지만, diffusion
but the way that we're going to do that in diffusion models
모델에서 그 방법은
is totally different.
완전히 다릅니다.
GANs learn this deterministic mapping
GAN은 생성기를 통해 z를
through the generator to map a z directly to an x.
직접 x로 매핑하는 결정론적 함수를 학습합니다.
With a diffusion model, we're going
diffusion 모델에서는
to do something more implicit, more indirect.
좀 더 암묵적이고 간접적인 방식을 사용합니다.
So what we're going to do, first off the first constraint
먼저 diffusion 모델의 첫
in diffusion models is that the z, the noise distribution,
번째 제약은 z, 즉 노이즈 분포가 항상
the noise always has to have the same shape as our data.
데이터와 같은 형태를 가져야 한다는 것입니다.
So if you have an image that's H by W by 3,
그래서 이미지가 H 곱하기 W 곱하기 3이라면,
then your noise distribution always
노이즈 분포도 항상 H 곱하기
has to be H by W by 3 as well.
W 곱하기 3이어야 합니다.
They have to be exactly the same shape.
모양이 정확히 같아야 합니다.
Now what we're going to do is consider different versions
이제 우리는 점점 더 많은 노이즈 수준으로 손상된
of our data that are corrupted by increasing levels of noise.
데이터의 다양한 버전을 고려할 것입니다.
So here, if we have a data sample, which
여기서 데이터
is this picture of a cat, then t is
샘플이 고양이 사진이라면, t는 0에서
going to be our noise level, which ranges from 0 to 1.
1까지 범위의 노이즈 수준이 됩니다.
So at t equals 0 that means no noise.
t가 0이라는 것은 노이즈가 없다는 뜻입니다.
That means a totally clean data sample.
즉, 완전히 깨끗한 데이터 샘플이라는 겁니다.
t equals 0.3 is a little bit of noise.
t가 0.3이면 약간의 노이즈가 있다는 뜻입니다.
We add some of our noise z into--
노이즈 z를 일부 데이터
we mix some of our noise, z, into our data, x.
x에 섞어서 넣는 거죠.
And if we go all the way to t equals 1, we get full noise.
t가 1까지 가면 완전한 노이즈가 됩니다.
And those are going to be samples directly
그것들은 노이즈 분포에서
from our noise distribution.
직접 뽑은 샘플이 될 겁니다.
So somehow this t parameter is going to interpolate smoothly
어떤 식으로든 이 t 파라미터가 데이터 분포와
between our data distribution and our noise distribution.
노이즈 분포 사이를 부드럽게 보간할 겁니다.
And this is something that we can--
그리고 이건 우리가 할
and the noise distribution again is
수 있는 것이고, 노이즈
going to be almost always Gaussian, Something simple
분포는 거의 항상 Gaussian, 즉 우리가
that we understand and can sample from.
이해하고 샘플링할 수 있는 단순한 분포입니다.
And now what we're going to do is train a neural network
이제 신경망을 훈련시켜서 점진적으로
to do a little bit of incremental denoising.
노이즈를 제거하도록 할 겁니다.
So the neural network is going to receive some sample, which
신경망은 중간 정도의 노이즈가 섞인 데이터
is a piece of data which has been corrupted
샘플을
with some intermediate amount of noise.
입력으로 받습니다.
And now the neural network is going
그리고 신경망은
to be trained to try to clean it up a little bit,
그 노이즈를 조금
remove just a little bit of noise.
제거하도록 훈련될 겁니다.
So the training objective here is
훈련 목표는
going to be neural network inputs, an image of some amount
신경망이 노이즈가 섞인 이미지를 입력받아
with some amount of noise and it tries
일부 노이즈를
to remove some of the noise.
제거하는 것입니다.
Then at inference time what we're going to do
추론 시에는 노이즈
is do an iterative procedure where we first
분포 pz에서 직접 노이즈
draw a noise sample directly from our noise distribution, pz,
샘플을 뽑고, 신경망을 반복 적용해
and then iteratively apply the neural network
한 번에 조금씩
to remove noise from that sample one at a time.
노이즈를 제거하는 절차를 수행합니다.
So the very first time we do this,
처음에는 완전한
we're going to draw a complete sample that's complete noise.
노이즈 샘플을 뽑습니다.
And then the very first application
그리고 신경망의 첫
of the neural network, the network
적용에서는 완전한
will be trying to remove noise from full noise.
노이즈에서 노이즈를 제거하려고 시도합니다.
So it will basically be forced to hallucinate
즉, 노이즈 속에서 아주
just a tiny whiff of data structure in that noise.
작은 데이터 구조를 상상해내야 하는 거죠.
And then once we get to some slightly less noisy example,
조금 덜 노이즈가 섞인
we're going to pass it back to the neural network
샘플이 되면
and again ask it to remove just a little bit of noise
다시 신경망에 넣어 조금
from this now slightly denoised, slightly generated image.
더 노이즈를 제거하도록 합니다.
And then it'll get a little bit less noisy
점점 덜 노이즈가 섞이고,
and it'll get a little bit less noisy,
또 덜 노이즈가
little bit less noisy.
섞이고, 계속 그렇게 됩니다.
And eventually, if we set up all of this stuff correctly,
모든 설정이 제대로 되면,
then we want to get to a situation
완전한 노이즈
where we can draw a complete noise sample
샘플을 뽑고 신경망에
and then ask the network to remove
노이즈를
noise from that complete sample z of complete random noise
제거하도록 반복해서 결국 모든 노이즈를
until eventually, we've removed all the noise
제거해 시스템에서 생성된
and come up with a generated sample from the system.
샘플을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So that's a weird setting.
이건 좀 이상한 설정입니다.
It's a weird thing, but that's the intuition
이게 바로 diffusion 모델의
behind diffusion models.
직관입니다.
Is the number of steps a fixed hyperparameter?
스텝 수가 고정된 하이퍼파라미터인가요?
It depends.
그건 경우에 따라 다릅니다.
So on this slide, I've intentionally been--
이 슬라이드에서는
I was forced to be very vague about all these things.
일부러 매우 모호하게 설명했습니다.
What is the noise?
노이즈가 무엇인지,
What does it mean to corrupt the data with respect to the noise?
데이터를 노이즈로 오염시키는 게 무슨 의미인지,
What does it mean to remove a little bit of the noise?
노이즈를 조금 제거하는 게 무슨 의미인지,
What does it mean to apply it iteratively at inference?
추론 시 반복 적용하는 게 무슨 의미인지,
Because, like I said, there's so many different formalisms
diffusion에는 다양한
of diffusion, there's a lot of different variants
형식과 변형이 많아서
about exactly what these mean in different situations.
상황에 따라 의미가 다릅니다.
So this slide is intended to be a fairly high level
이 슬라이드는 diffusion의 큰 그림을
overview of diffusion.
보여주기 위한 것입니다.
And then different specific implementations
그리고 diffusion
of diffusion models will have different concrete choices
모델의 구체적 구현마다 이
for what all these terms specifically mean.
용어들의 의미가 다를 수 있습니다.
So does this high level picture of diffusion make sense?
이 diffusion의 큰 그림이 이해가 되시나요?
OK, so then let's make this more concrete.
좋습니다, 그러면 좀 더 구체적으로 들어가 보겠습니다.
So now we're going to jump from general diffusion models
이제 일반 diffusion 모델에서
to a particular category of diffusion models called
rectified flow 모델이라는 특정
rectified flow models.
범주로 넘어가겠습니다.
Some people may argue with me and say that rectified flow is
어떤 분들은 rectified flow가 diffusion이 아니라고
not diffusion.
주장할 수도 있습니다.
Some people might say that they're different things.
어떤 분들은 둘이 다르다고 말할 수도 있죠.
I don't really care.
저는 별로 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
To me, rectified flow is a kind of diffusion model.
저에게 rectified flow는 일종의 diffusion model입니다.
Fight me.
한번 싸워보시죠.
So with rectified flow, the intuition is basically this.
그래서 rectified flow의 직관은 기본적으로 이렇습니다.
We have the same thing.
우리는 같은 것을 가지고 있습니다.
We have our pnoise.
우리는 pnoise를 가지고 있습니다.
We have our pdata.
우리는 pdata를 가지고 있습니다.
And we're going to draw this geometrically
그리고 저는 이것을 기하학적으로 그릴
because I think that's a nice way to gain intuition.
건데, 직관을 얻기에 좋은 방법이라고 생각합니다.
Geometrically in two dimensions in particular because that's
특히 2차원에서 기하학적으로 그릴 텐데,
all that fits on the slide, but of course,
그게 슬라이드에 다 들어가기
these are going to be super, super high dimensional images
때문입니다. 물론 실제로는 이
and Gaussians, which is an easy way
이미지들과 가우시안은 매우
to get led astray because you know that intuitions that hold
고차원입니다. 2차원, 3차원에서 통하는 직관이
in two and three dimensions go totally out the window
고차원에서는 완전히 통하지 않기 때문에
when you go to a lot of dimensions.
쉽게 오해할 수 있습니다.
It's really sad.
정말 안타깝죠.
It's sad that we live in such a low dimensional universe
우리가 이렇게 저차원 우주에 살고 있다는
because our intuitions that we build in this universe just
게 안타깝습니다. 이 우주에서 만든
don't really transfer to 100 dimensional spaces,
직관이 100차원, 1000차원 공간에는 잘
1,000 dimensional spaces.
적용되지 않으니까요.
So always be aware, but it is what it is.
항상 이 점을 유념하세요, 하지만 어쩔 수 없습니다.
We're stuck with the universe we got.
우리는 가진 우주에 갇혀 있습니다.
So the setup in rectified flow is
그래서 rectified flow의
that we've got our distribution pnoise, our distribution pdata.
설정은 pnoise 분포와 pdata 분포를 가지고 있다는 겁니다.
pnoise is something simple that we
pnoise는 우리가 이해하고
understand we can sample from, we can compute integrals of.
샘플링할 수 있으며 적분도 계산할 수 있는 단순한 분포입니다.
It's a very friendly distribution. pdata again,
아주 친근한 분포죠. pdata는 다시 말해 복잡한
is something crazy.
분포입니다.
That's what the universe is using to give us images.
우주가 우리에게 이미지를 주기 위해 사용하는 분포입니다.
Now at every training iteration, we're
이제 매 학습 반복마다,
going to sample a z from our prior distribution and sample
우리는 prior 분포에서 z를 샘플링하고 데이터
an x from our data distribution.
분포에서 x를 샘플링할 겁니다.
We can draw a sample analytically
pz는 우리가 제어하는 단순한
because pz is something simple that we control.
분포이기 때문에 샘플을 해석적으로 그릴 수 있습니다.
And drawing a sample from the data distribution
데이터 분포에서 샘플을 그린다는 건
just means picking an example from your finite training set.
유한한 학습 세트에서 예제를 고르는 것을 의미합니다.
Now and you're also going to choose a t
그리고 0에서 1 사이에서 균등하게
to be uniform on 0 to 1.
t를 선택할 겁니다.
Remember t is our noise level, where t equals 0 means no noise,
t는 노이즈 레벨로, t=0은 노이즈 없음,
t equals 1 means all the noise.
t=1은 완전 노이즈 상태입니다.
So now we're going to draw a line
이제 데이터 샘플 x에서
that points from our data sample x directly to our noise sample
노이즈 샘플 z로 향하는 선을 그릴
z.
겁니다.
And this line, this vector pointing from x to z,
이 선, 즉 x에서 z로 향하는
we're going to call it v. This is going to be
벡터를 v라고 부르겠습니다. 이것이 flow field의
the velocity of a flow field.
속도 벡터가 됩니다.
And then we set xt to be a point along this line, which
그리고 xt는 이 선 위의 한 점으로, x와
is a linear interpolation between x and z.
z 사이의 선형 보간입니다.
So now we've got our noise sample
그래서 이제 노이즈 샘플
z, our data sample x, we've got the velocity
z, 데이터 샘플 x, 그 사이의
vector between them, v, and we've picked
속도 벡터 v, 그리고 노이즈 버전의
a noise version of our data xt.
데이터 xt를 갖게 되었습니다.
And in the previous slide when we said get noisy data,
이전 슬라이드에서 '노이즈가 있는 데이터 얻기'라고 했을 때, rectified
this is what that means in the case of rectified flow models.
flow 모델에서는 이것이 의미하는 바입니다.
It's a linear interpolation between a data
데이터 샘플과 노이즈 샘플
sample and a noise sample.
사이의 선형 보간입니다.
And now the training objective is very, very simple.
이제 학습 목표는 매우 간단합니다.
So now we're going to train a neural network f theta,
이제 학습 가능한 파라미터 theta를 가진
so that's f with learnable parameters theta.
신경망 f theta를 학습할 겁니다.
That neural network is going to input the noisy sample xt as
그 신경망은 노이즈가 있는 샘플 xt와 노이즈 레벨
well as the noise level t.
t를 입력으로 받습니다.
And it's going to try to predict the green vector v.
그리고 초록색 벡터 v를 예측하려고 합니다.
So that's it.
그게 전부입니다.
That's all we need to do in rectified flow.
rectified flow에서 우리가 해야 할 일은 그것뿐입니다.
The code for this is very simple.
이 코드가 매우 간단합니다.
You would be shocked how much obscurity there
여기 논문을 읽으면 얼마나 난해한지
is when you read papers here.
깜짝 놀랄 겁니다.
And it boils down to this very simple code.
하지만 결국 이 아주 간단한 코드로 요약됩니다.
Drives me crazy that this is not made
많은 발표에서 이 부분이 더
more clear in a lot of presentations of this.
명확하게 설명되지 않는 게 정말 답답합니다.
So then the training loop for rectified flow
그래서 rectified flow의
is extremely simple.
학습 루프는 매우 간단합니다.
You loop over your data set at every iteration.
매 반복마다 데이터셋을 순회합니다.
You get z, which is unit Gaussian of the same shape as x.
x와 같은 형태의 단위 가우시안 z를 얻습니다.
You choose a noise level t, which is uniform 0 to 1.
0에서 1 사이의 균등 분포에서 노이즈 레벨 t를 선택합니다.
You compute xt, which is a linear interpolation between x
x와 z 사이를 선형 보간하여 xt를
and z.
계산합니다.
You give xt and t to your model and then
xt와 t를 모델에 입력하고,
your loss is just the mean squared error
손실은 이 실제값
between this ground truth v and the model prediction.
v와 모델 예측 간의 평균 제곱 오차입니다.
And that's it.
그게 전부입니다.
That's your training objective for rectified flow models.
이것이 rectified flow 모델의 학습 목표입니다.
Contrast this with GANs.
GAN과 비교해 보겠습니다.
When you train rectified flow models or really
정류 흐름 모델이나 사실상 모든 종류의
any kind of diffusion model, you have
확산 모델을 훈련할 때, 훈련 중에
a loss that you can look at during training.
볼 수 있는 손실 함수가 있습니다.
When the loss goes down, the model is generally better.
손실이 줄어들면 모델이 일반적으로 더 좋아집니다.
So for those of us that went through half a decade of GAN
그래서 GAN 광풍을 반년 넘게 겪은
madness, the first time you train a diffusion model
우리에게, 확산 모델을 처음 훈련하고
and there's a loss to look at, it's like, oh my god,
손실을 볼 수 있다는 건, 와, 정말
this is an amazing thing.
놀라운 일입니다.
How many hours have we spent looking at GAN plots and they
우리가 GAN 플롯을 몇 시간이나 봤는데,
look like this?
이런 모양이었죠?
And you have no idea.
그리고 전혀 알 수가 없었습니다.
It's like reading tea leaves to tell whether or not
모델이 잘 작동하는지 차잎을
the model is working well.
읽는 것 같았습니다.
You train a diffusion model, you get
확산 모델을 훈련하면,
this beautiful, smooth exponential loss curve
아름답고 부드러운
and it just makes you so happy, so that's great.
지수 손실 곡선을 얻어서 정말 기쁩니다. 정말 좋죠.
So then that's training for that's
이게 확산 모델
training for diffusion models.
훈련입니다.
Now what do we do at inference because the GANs are
그럼 추론 단계에서는 어떻게 할까요? GAN은 추론이
kind of easy at inference?
꽤 쉽습니다.
GANs, you just have to take a z, pass it through your generator.
GAN은 그냥 z를 받아서 생성기에 통과시키면 됩니다.
You get a data sample.
데이터 샘플을 얻죠.
Very straightforward, but now with diffusion model
매우 간단합니다. 하지만 확산
or rectified flow model in this case, the model output
모델이나 이 경우 정류 흐름 모델에서는 모델
itself is useless.
출력 자체가 쓸모가 없습니다.
We get this xt.
xt를 얻고,
We get a v. What are we going to do with this?
v를 얻습니다. 이걸 가지고 무엇을 할까요?
Not super clear.
그다지 명확하지 않습니다.
So then at inference time is where
그래서 추론 시점에서
diffusion models get a little bit more
diffusion
complicated compared to GANs.
모델은 GAN보다 좀 더 복잡해집니다.
So at inference we first will upfront
추론 시에는 먼저 보통 고정된
choose a number of steps, t, which
상수인 단계 수
is usually a fixed constant.
t를 정합니다.
And in the case of rectified flow models,
rectified flow
t equals 50 is usually a good number to start with.
모델의 경우 보통 t=50이 적당한 시작점입니다.
Sometimes you can get down to t equals 30 and that works OK.
때로는 t=30까지 줄여도 괜찮습니다.
Then what you're going to do is sample an x directly
그다음에는 노이즈 분포에서 직접
from your noise distribution.
x를 샘플링합니다.
This is going to be pure noise that's sampled from your known
이것은 알려진 노이즈 분포에서
noise distribution.
샘플링한 순수 노이즈입니다.
Then you're going to evaluate the-- then you're
그다음에는 t=1부터
going to loop from t equals 1.
루프를 돌립니다.
You're going to march backwards to t equals 0.
t=0까지 역순으로 진행합니다.
This is your noise level.
이것이 노이즈 레벨입니다.
And in this case in this simple version
이 간단한 버전에서는
we're just marching linearly from full noise 1 back
완전 노이즈 1에서 완전 깨끗한
to noise 0 perfectly clean.
노이즈 0으로 선형적으로 진행합니다.
Then at the first iteration we're
첫 번째 반복에서는
going to take our xt that was at first full noise,
처음에 완전 노이즈였던 xt를 현재 노이즈 레벨과
pass it to the network along with the current noise level
함께 네트워크에 넣어 네트워크가
and get the network's predicted vt.
예측한 vt를 얻습니다.
And remember what this vt is supposed to be
rectified flow의 경우 이 vt가
in the case of rectified flow.
무엇을 의미하는지 기억하세요.
This v, remember, was supposed to point from a data sample
이 v는 데이터 샘플에서 노이즈 샘플로 향하는
all the way to a noise sample.
벡터여야 합니다.
So then it's geometrically obvious
그래서 rectified flow의
what you should do in the case of rectified flow.
경우 기하학적으로 무엇을 해야 할지 명확합니다.
You should take a little step along that
예측된 v 벡터를 따라 조금
predicted v vector because the problem is, this rectified flow
이동해야 합니다. 문제는 이 rectified flow 모델의
model, that v is not going to point you
v가 깨끗한 샘플까지 완전히 가리키지
all the way to a clean sample.
않는다는 점입니다.
It's just going to get you started.
그저 시작점만 알려줄 뿐입니다.
It's going to set you on a trajectory
깨끗한 샘플로 가는
towards a clean sample.
경로를 설정해주는 거죠.
So we take a little step along that predicted v from the flow
그래서 flow 모델이 예측한 v를
model to get a new x2, which is now a version of the data that
따라 조금 이동해 새로운 x2를 얻습니다. 이 x2는
has had a little bit of the noise removed
모델이 노이즈를 조금
from it by the model.
제거한 데이터 버전입니다.
And now we iterate this.
그리고 이 과정을 반복합니다.
So once we have this x two thirds,
x2를 얻으면 다시 모델에
then we pass it back to the model
넣어 또
and get another predicted v vector from the model.
다른 예측된 v 벡터를 얻습니다.
And remember the v is supposed to point from a clean sample
v는 깨끗한 샘플에서 노이즈 샘플로 향하는 벡터여야 한다는
all the way to a noise sample.
점을 기억하세요.
So then again, we can take a gradient step,
그래서 다시 이 예측된
take a little step along this predicted v
v를 따라 조금
to get another x one third.
이동해 x1을 얻습니다.
Repeat this thing again.
이 과정을 반복합니다.
Evaluate the model again to get another predicted v
모델을 평가해 또 다른 예측된
and then take a step in this case all the way to no noise
v를 얻고, 이번에는 노이즈가
all the way to the end of that vector to get our predicted x0.
전혀 없는 끝점까지 이동해 x0를 얻습니다.
And then that is our sample from our diffusion model.
이 x0가 diffusion 모델에서의 샘플입니다.
So then the inference procedure you
그래서 여기서 보시는 추론
see here got a little bit more complicated compared to GANs,
절차는 GAN보다 좀 더
but what we gained here was sanity.
복잡하지만, 얻은 것은 안정성입니다.
When you're training you've regained
학습할 때 안정성을
that and they tend to give you much better samples
되찾았고, 훨씬 더 좋은 샘플을
and they tend to scale really well to large data
내며 대규모 데이터셋과
sets and large models.
모델에도 잘 확장됩니다.
And the code here is really simple.
코드는 매우 간단합니다.
So we start off by taking a random sample,
무작위 샘플을 완전히 랜덤하게
make it be perfectly random, then march backwards
시작하고, t=1부터 0까지
for t from 1 back to 0.
역순으로 진행합니다.
At every noise level, you get a predicted v
각 노이즈 레벨에서
from the model, given your current sample as well
현재 샘플과 t를 입력으로
as your T. Then you take what looks like a gradient descent
모델이 예측한 v를 얻습니다. 그다음 모델이 예측한 v에 대해 경사 하강법
step on the model's predicted v and update the sample
스텝처럼 보이는 작은 이동을 하고 샘플을
and just repeat this whole thing in a loop.
업데이트하며 이 과정을 반복합니다.
So then you can see these diffusion models
그래서 결국 이 diffusion 모델들이 그렇게 무섭지
aren't so scary after all.
않다는 걸 알 수 있습니다.
You can actually fit a complete implementation
사실 rectified flow
of training and sampling from a rectified flow
모델의 학습과 샘플링을 완전히 구현한
model in just a couple lines on one slide,
코드를 한 슬라이드에 몇 줄로 간단히 표현할 수 있는데,
which I think is very nice.
저는 이 점이 아주 좋다고 생각합니다.
OK, so you might be asked-- so this is pretty nice.
좋습니다, 그래서 아마 이런 질문을 받을 수도 있겠네요-- 꽤 괜찮습니다.
I'm pretty happy that we're able to get to a full--
전체 구현까지 도달할 수 있어서 저는 꽤 만족스럽습니다-- 그리고
and this will actually work.
이 코드는 실제로 작동할 겁니다.
If you take this code, you plug it in,
이 코드를 가져다가 적절한
you plug it in a reasonable model architecture,
모델 아키텍처에 적용하면 실제로 작동할
this will actually work.
수 있습니다.
This will actually convert to something
많은 경우에 이것이 합리적인
reasonable in a lot of cases.
결과로 변환될 겁니다.
You're hitting on the core problem in generative modeling
여러분이 지금 짚고 있는 부분이 바로 제가 지난 며칠간
that I've been thinking about a lot the last couple of days
이 슬라이드를 보면서 많이 고민했던
while reviewing these slides.
생성 모델링의 핵심 문제입니다.
The core problem in generative modeling
생성 모델링의 핵심
is somehow you have a prior distribution, which
문제는, 샘플링할 수 있는 prior
is z's that you know how to sample from.
분포인 z가 있고,
You have a data distribution, which is
생성하고자 하는 데이터 분포인
x's that you want to generate.
x가 있다는 점입니다.
And the core problem in generative modeling
그리고 생성 모델링의 핵심
is figuring out how to associate z's and x's and all
문제는 z와 x를 어떻게 연관 짓느냐인데,
your different categories to generative modeling
다양한 생성 모델링 방법들이
do it in different ways.
이를 다르게 해결합니다.
In a VAE, you say I'm going to have the model predict a z
VAE에서는 모델이 z를 예측하고 그 다음 x를 예측하도록
and then predict an x and then try to force that z
하면서, 그 z가 샘플링할 수 있는 분포가
to be something I know how to sample from,
되도록 강제하는데, 이 방법은
which doesn't super work that well.
그렇게 잘 작동하지 않습니다.
In a GAN you're not supervising that relationship.
GAN에서는 그 관계를 감독하지 않습니다.
The generator is kind of figuring out
생성자는 discriminator가
its own mapping from z to x in a feedforward way
주는 분포 매칭 목표를 통해 feedforward
through this distribution matching objective
방식으로 z에서 x로의
that the discriminator is giving it.
매핑을 스스로 찾아내는 거죠.
In diffusion, it's figuring out by--
diffusion 모델에서는 결국 이 곡선들을
it ends up having to integrate these curves.
적분하는 방식으로 해결합니다.
And there's actually several different mathematical
그리고 이런 목표 함수들이 확률 분포를
formalisms as to why objectives that look like this
합리적으로 맞추는 이유에 대해
end up matching probability distributions
여러 수학적 형식들이
in a reasonable way.
존재합니다.
But again, the whole core problem
하지만 다시 말해, 핵심 문제는
is that we have no way ahead of time
prior에서 샘플링한 z와 데이터에서
to pair up samples z from our prior with samples
샘플링한 x를 미리 짝지을 방법이
x from our data.
없다는 점입니다.
If we knew how to make that pairing
만약 우리가 그 쌍을 만드는
and also knew how to sample from the prior, you'd be done.
방법과 사전 분포에서 샘플링하는 방법을 안다면, 끝난 겁니다.
And in some sense, all these different forms
어떤 의미에서는, 이러한
of generative modeling are different ways
다양한 형태의 생성 모델링이
to square that circle and come up
모두 그 문제를 해결하고
with a way to learn an association from z to x
z에서 x로의 연관성을 학습하며, 훈련 시점에 그 연관성이
and be able to sample from z even
없어도 z에서 샘플링할 수
though we don't have that association at training time.
있는 방법을 찾는 다양한 방식입니다.
There's a lot of different interpretations
이것에 대한 해석이
of this that can get very, very heavy, very quick
매우 복잡해질 수 있어서
so I've tried to avoid them.
저는 그런 부분은 피하려고 했습니다.
But we said last lecture that unconditional generative
하지만 지난 강의에서 무조건적인 생성 모델링은 무의미하다고
modeling is pointless, so what we almost always
했으니, 우리가 거의 항상 관심 있는 것은
care about is conditional generative modeling.
조건부 생성 모델링입니다.
And that's easy to accommodate in rectified flow.
그리고 이것은 rectified flow에서 쉽게 적용할 수 있습니다.
So to do conditional rectified flow,
조건부 rectified flow를
we imagine that there's different subparts of our data
하려면, 데이터 분포에 여러 하위 부분이 있다고
distribution.
상상하면 됩니다.
Here I'm saying it's categorical.
여기서는 범주형이라고 말하는 거죠.
Maybe our data is actually squares and triangles.
우리 데이터가 실제로는 정사각형과 삼각형일 수도 있습니다.
And then we have our whole data distribution pdata as well as
그리고 전체 데이터 분포 pdata와 두
our two subdistributions, pdata x given that y is a square
개의 하위 분포, 즉 y가 정사각형일 때의 pdata
and pdata x given that the label y is a triangle.
x와 y가 삼각형일 때의 pdata x가 있습니다.
So this is the picture you should have in mind
이것이 조건부 생성 모델링을
when you think about conditional generative modeling.
생각할 때 머릿속에 떠올려야 할 그림입니다.
Then in the case of rectified flow
그럼 rectified flow의
this is very easy to accommodate.
경우에는 이것을 매우 쉽게 적용할 수 있습니다.
So your data set now has pairs x and y
데이터 세트에는 이제 x와 y 쌍이 있고,
and your model now takes y as an additional auxiliary input
모델은 y를 추가 보조 입력으로
somehow.
받습니다.
And then during sampling same thing.
샘플링할 때도 마찬가지입니다.
You get your predicted V's.
예측된 V들을 얻습니다.
The model takes as input this extra y and you use that.
모델은 이 추가 y를 입력으로 받고, 그것을 사용합니다.
So this all goes through.
이 모든 과정이 그대로 진행됩니다.
The difference is that now y is actually
차이점은 이제 y가 실제로 사용자가
hopefully some conditional signal
제어할 수 있는 어떤
that the user can control.
조건부 신호라는 점입니다.
Maybe this is a text prompt.
아마도 이것은 텍스트 프롬프트일 수 있습니다.
Maybe this is an input image.
아마도 이것은 입력 이미지일 수 있습니다.
Maybe this is some kind of user input
아마도 이것은 추론 시에 기대하는
that you're expecting at inference time, which
어떤 사용자 입력일 수 있는데,
actually make these models controllable and useful
이것이 실제로 이 모델들을 제어
in practice.
가능하고 실용적으로 만드는 겁니다.
But then there's another really interesting question.
하지만 또 다른 정말 흥미로운 질문이 있습니다.
Is there any knob you can tune to control
모델이 조건 신호에 얼마나 집중할지
how much the model pays attention to the conditioning
조절할 수 있는 노브가
signal?
있을까요?
It turns out if you train these things naively,
알고 보니 이런 모델들을 단순히
a lot of times they don't often follow the conditioning
훈련시키면, 원하는 만큼 조건 신호를
signal quite as much as you would like.
잘 따르지 않는 경우가 많습니다.
So there's a trick called classifier free guidance
그래서 classifier free
or CFG that changes our diffusion training
guidance, 줄여서 CFG라는 트릭이 있는데, 이것은 우리의 diffusion 훈련
loop just a little bit.
루프를 조금 바꿉니다.
So what we're going to do is we're still
그래서 우리가 할
going to train this conditional diffusion model that
일은 여전히 xt와 y를
inputs your xt, inputs your y, but on every training iteration,
입력으로 받는 조건부 diffusion 모델을 훈련시키되, 매 훈련 반복마다
we're going to flip a coin.
동전을 던지는 겁니다.
And if that coin is heads we're going to delete the conditioning
동전이 앞면이면 조건 정보를
information.
삭제합니다.
So we're going to set it equal to some kind of 0
즉, 조건 정보를 0값이나
value or null value, basically destroy the conditioning
널 값으로 설정해서 50% 확률로
information 50% of the time.
조건 정보를 없애는 거죠.
That could be a hyperparameter, but 50 is a pretty good one
이 확률은 하이퍼파라미터가 될 수 있지만, 50%가
that most people use in practice.
대부분 실무에서 좋은 값입니다.
So we're going to flip a coin.
그래서 동전을 던집니다.
If the coin is heads, delete the conditioning information.
동전이 앞면이면 조건 정보를 삭제합니다.
So that means that the model is conceptually
이 말은 모델이 개념적으로 두
now forced to learn two different kinds of velocity
가지 다른 속도 벡터를 배우도록 강제된다는
vectors.
뜻입니다.
So then the model is forced to learn two different kinds
그래서 모델은 두 가지 다른 속도 벡터를
of velocity vectors.
배우도록 강제됩니다.
So in the case where we pass it this null value for y that
그래서 y에 대해 조건 정보를 파괴한 null 값을
has destroyed the conditioning information,
전달하는 경우에는, 이것이
then this is basically an unconditional generative model
기본적으로 무조건 생성 모델이
now.
됩니다.
Now that predicted velocity vector, v, has to point back
예측된 속도 벡터 v는 전체 데이터 분포
towards the meat of the whole data distribution pdata,
pdata의 중심을 향해야 하는데, 실제 조건
but when we pass a real conditioning input
입력 y를 전달하면, 즉 파괴되지
y that's not destroyed, non-null, non-zero,
않고 null도 0도 아닌 경우에는,
then we're getting a conditional velocity vector that
전체 데이터 분포가 아니라
is pointing us back towards not the full data distribution,
우리가 관심 있는 조건 신호에 따른
but towards the conditional data distribution, which
조건부 데이터 분포를 향하는
is conditional on that conditioning signal
조건부 속도
that we cared about.
벡터를 얻는 겁니다.
And then the dumb trick is we're going
그리고 간단한 트릭은
to take a linear combination of these two vectors
이 두 벡터의 선형 결합을
to push it more towards the conditional velocity vector.
취해서 조건부 속도 벡터 쪽으로 더 밀어주는 겁니다.
So in particular we'll have a scalar hyperparameter w
특히 스칼라 하이퍼파라미터 w를 두고,
and take a linear combination 1 plus times
1+w 곱하기 vy에서 w
vy minus w times v null.
곱하기 v null을 뺀 선형 결합을 취합니다.
So that's going to be a vector that
이렇게 하면
now points even more towards the conditional distribution
이제 데이터 분포보다 조건부 분포를 더 향하는
than it does the data distribution.
벡터가 됩니다.
And then the idea is that during sampling we're now going to--
그리고 샘플링할 때는 이제 모델이
then during sampling, we're now going
예측한 원래
to step according to this v CFG vector rather
벡터 대신 이 v CFG 벡터에 따라 한 스텝씩
than the raw vectors predicted by the model.
이동하는 겁니다.
And then setting w equals 1--
그리고 여기서 w를 0으로 설정하면
setting w equals 0 here, we'll recover exactly
정확히 조건부 1을
the conditional 1.
복원할 수 있습니다.
And the higher your w is then the more
w가 클수록 조건 신호를 더
you're overemphasizing the conditioning signal.
과도하게 강조하는 겁니다.
And then this is pretty easy to implement.
이 방법은 구현하기 꽤 쉽습니다.
So then your inference code doesn't really change too much,
그래서 추론 코드는 크게 바뀌지 않지만, 매
but now you evaluate the model twice at every iteration
반복마다 모델을 두 번
to get your vy and your v0.
평가해서 vy와 v0를 얻고,
And then you take this linear combination
그다음 이 선형 결합을 취해서 그에
and then step according to that.
따라 한 스텝 이동하는 겁니다.
And this is called classifier free because of a stupid reason.
이 방법을 classifier free라고 부르는데, 사실 좀 어처구니없는 이유 때문입니다.
There was an earlier paper called classifier guidance
이전에 classifier guidance라는 논문이 있었는데,
that I don't want to get into.
그건 자세히 다루고 싶지 않습니다.
And then they removed the classifier.
그리고 나서 분류기를 제거했죠.
And even though there was only nine months between those two
두 논문 사이에 9개월밖에 안 됐고 두 번째
papers and it's now been four years since the second one,
논문이 나온 지 4년이 지났지만, 우리는 아직도 classifier
we're still stuck with the name classifier free guidance.
free guidance라는 이름을 쓰고 있습니다.
So it is what it is.
그냥 그런 겁니다.
OK, so that's actually really important in practice
좋습니다, 실제로 고품질 출력을
for getting high quality outputs and that's CFG.
얻기 위해 매우 중요한 것이 바로 CFG입니다.
That's really important.
이것은 정말 중요합니다.
That's used everywhere in diffusion models.
확산 모델 어디에서나 사용됩니다.
It does double the cost of sampling though because now you
하지만 샘플링 비용이 두 배가
need to hit the model twice on every iteration, which
되는데, 매 반복마다 모델을 두 번
is a problem.
호출해야 하기 때문입니다. 이게 문제죠.
There's this thing on optimal prediction.
최적 예측에 관한 내용이 있습니다.
I think I'll skip that.
그 부분은 건너뛰겠습니다.
That's not so interesting.
그다지 흥미롭지 않습니다.
It is interesting, but I'm worried about time.
흥미롭긴 한데 시간이 걱정되네요.
But one thing that we sometimes need to do
하지만 때때로 t
is tweak this t distribution.
분포를 조정해야 할 때가 있습니다.
So we saw in particular that we were sampling t
특히 원시 rectified
according to a uniform distribution
flow 모델에서 t를 균등 분포에
in a raw rectified flow model.
따라 샘플링하는 것을 봤습니다.
And the thing about that is that is
그런데 이 방식은 모든 노이즈
going to put uniform emphasis on all noise levels.
레벨에 균등한 비중을 둔다는 점입니다.
And intuitively, when you're at full noise,
직관적으로, 노이즈가 가득한
the problem is very easy.
상태에서는 문제가 매우 쉽습니다.
When you're at full noise,
노이즈가 가득한 상태에서는 문제가 매우 쉽습니다.
Then the optimal prediction from the model
그때 모델의 최적 예측은 기본적으로
is basically to point towards the mean of the data
데이터 분포의 평균을
distribution.
가리키는 것입니다.
And similarly, when you're at 0 noise
마찬가지로, 노이즈가 0일 때 최적
then the optimal prediction is actually
예측은 실제로 노이즈
to point towards the mean of the noise distribution.
분포의 평균을 가리키는 것입니다.
So actually the optimal prediction
그래서 실제로 모델의 최적 예측은 노이즈가
from the model at full noise and full data and no noise
가득한 상태와 데이터가 완전한 상태, 즉 노이즈가 없는 상태 모두
are actually very relatively easy problems.
상대적으로 매우 쉬운 문제입니다.
It just needs to learn the mean of those two distributions.
그냥 두 분포의 평균을 배우면 됩니다.
But when you're somewhere in the middle,
하지만 중간 어딘가에 있을
it's actually really hard because when
때는 실제로 매우 어렵습니다. 왜냐하면
you're somewhere in the middle and you sample that xt,
중간 어딘가에 있고 xt를 샘플링할
there might have been multiple pairs x
때, 그 같은 xt를 만들
and z that could have given rise to that same xt in the middle.
수 있는 여러 쌍의 x와 z가 있을 수 있기 때문입니다.
And then the network basically needs
그래서 네트워크는 기본적으로
to solve this expectation problem
이 기대값 문제를
and figure out what is that optimal direction
해결해야 하고, 이 xt 지점에서 교차할
to predict that integrates over all possible x's and z's that
수 있는 모든 가능한 x와 z를 통합하는 최적의 예측 방향이
might intersect at this point xt.
무엇인지 알아내야 합니다.
So somehow those points in the middle are intuitively much
그래서 중간 지점의 포인트들은 직관적으로
harder for the network to solve, but when we sample uniformly
네트워크가 해결하기 훨씬 더 어렵지만, 0부터 1까지
from 0 to 1t, then we're putting equal importance on all levels
균일하게 샘플링하면 모든 노이즈 레벨에 동일한 중요도를
of noise, which doesn't really match this intuition.
부여하게 되어 이 직관과 맞지 않습니다.
So in practice you'll often sample
그래서 실제로는 종종 다른
from different noise schedules.
노이즈 스케줄에서 샘플링합니다.
And one very popular one is this one
그리고 매우 인기 있는 방법 중
called logit-normal sampling, which basically
하나가 logit-normal 샘플링인데, 기본적으로
looks like a Gaussian, puts relatively little weight
가우시안처럼 보이고 0과 1에는 상대적으로
on the 0 and the 1 with a lot more weight in the middle.
적은 가중치를 두고 중간에 더 많은 가중치를 둡니다.
Another thing you'll see sometimes
또 가끔 볼 수 있는 것은
are these so-called shifted noise schedules
비대칭적인 shifted noise
that are asymmetric that shift more towards one
schedules로, 한쪽 방향으로 더
direction or the other.
치우친 스케줄입니다.
And those are important as we scale to high resolution data.
이것들은 고해상도 데이터로 확장할 때 중요합니다.
The intuition being that when you have a very high resolution
직관적으로, 해상도가 매우 높은 이미지일 때는
image, then there can be very strong
인접한 픽셀들 간에 매우
correlations across neighboring pixels.
강한 상관관계가 있을 수 있습니다.
When you have a low resolution image,
해상도가 낮은 이미지일 때는
then the correlations across neighboring pixels
인접한 픽셀들 간의 상관관계가 더
tend to be smaller.
작아지는 경향이 있습니다.
So depending on how strong of correlations
그래서 데이터 내 상관관계의
you have in your data, you actually
강도에 따라 적절하게
may need different amounts of noise level
정보를 파괴하기 위해 필요한
to properly destroy information in a nice way.
노이즈 수준이 달라질 수 있습니다.
So these things don't naively scale to different resolutions.
이런 것들은 단순히 해상도에 맞춰서 조정되지 않습니다.
And that's actually a big problem with these diffusion
사실 이런 diffusion
models is that they're a beautiful formulation,
모델들의 큰 문제점 중 하나는, 매우 훌륭한
but they're hard to get them to work naively
수식화이지만 고해상도 데이터에
on high resolution data.
단순 적용하기 어렵다는 점입니다.
So that leads to actually--
그래서 실제로는—제가
I said diffusion models are the most popular form
diffusion 모델이 가장 인기 있는 생성
of generative modeling.
모델이라고 했는데,
That was a little bit of a lie, because what's actually
그건 약간 과장된 말이고, 실제로 가장
most popular are these so-called latent diffusion
인기 있는 것은 latent diffusion
models, which is a variant that actually gets used everywhere.
모델이라 불리는 변형으로, 이게 사실상 어디서나 사용됩니다.
So here it's going to be a multi-stage procedure.
여기서는 다단계 절차가 진행될 것입니다.
So what we're going to do is first train an encoder network
그래서 우리가 할 일은 먼저 인코더 네트워크와 디코더 네트워크를
and a decoder network.
훈련하는 것입니다.
The encoder network is going to map from our image
인코더 네트워크는 이미지를 잠재 공간으로
into some latent space, which I've colored in purple.
매핑하는 역할을 하며, 여기서는 보라색으로 표시했습니다.
And ideally that latent is going to spatially downsample
이 잠재 공간은 이상적으로 이미지의
the image by a factor of D, as well as convert from three
공간 해상도를 D배로 줄이고, 채널 수는
channels up into C channels.
3개에서 C개로 변환합니다.
And a pretty common setting is to get 8
일반적인 설정은 공간
by 8 spatial downsampling and to increase to 16 channels.
해상도를 8x8로 줄이고 채널 수를 16개로 늘리는 것입니다.
That's some of these most common encoder decoders.
이것이 가장 흔한 인코더-디코더 구조 중 하나입니다.
These encoder decoders tend to be CNNs with attention,
이 인코더-디코더들은 보통 CNN과 어텐션을
but some more recent papers have explored VITs for these.
결합한 형태지만, 최근 논문들은 VIT를 적용하기도 했습니다.
Then what we do is we're going to train a diffusion model not
그다음에 하는 것은, 원본 이미지의 픽셀
on the raw pixel space of our images,
공간이 아니라, 이 인코더-디코더
but instead on the latent space, which is discovered
모델이 발견한 잠재 공간에서
by this encoder decoder model.
확산 모델을 훈련하는 것입니다.
So then the training procedure looks for training the diffusion
그래서 확산 모델 훈련 절차는, 이미지를
model, we're going to sample an image,
샘플링하고, 1단계에서 학습한
pass it through the encoder that we learned in the first stage
인코더를 통해 잠재 표현을 얻은
to get a latent and then add noise to the latent
뒤, 그 잠재에 노이즈를 더하고, 확산
and train the diffusion model to denoise the noise latent.
모델이 노이즈가 섞인 잠재를 복원하도록 훈련하는 방식입니다.
And really importantly, you freeze the encoder
그리고 정말 중요한 점은, 인코더를
so you do not propagate the gradients back into the encoder.
고정(freeze)해서 인코더 쪽으로는 그래디언트가 역전파되지 않도록 한다는 겁니다.
We're only using it to extract these latents
우리는 인코더가 학습한 잠재 공간(latent space)에서
and then training a diffusion model directly
직접 확산 모델(diffusion model)을
on the latent space, which is learned by the encoder.
학습하기 위해 잠재 표현만 추출하는 데 인코더를 사용합니다.
Then at inference time, once you're all done training,
그다음 추론 시에는, 학습이 모두 끝나면
then we'll sample a random latent pass it
무작위 잠재 벡터를 샘플링해서 확산
through the diffusion model many, many times to remove
모델에 여러 번 통과시켜 모든 노이즈를
all the noise to get a clean sample,
제거해 깨끗한 샘플을 얻는데,
but that clean sample is now a clean sample in latent space.
그 깨끗한 샘플은 잠재 공간에서의 깨끗한 샘플입니다.
So then we need to run the decoder
그래서 그 깨끗한 잠재 표현을
to convert that clean latent into a clean image.
깨끗한 이미지로 변환하려면 디코더를 실행해야 합니다.
And this is actually the most common form
사실 이것이 요즘 대부분의
of most diffusion models these days.
확산 모델에서 가장 일반적인 형태입니다.
So you might be asking OK we've knocked this diffusion
그래서 여러분은 아마 이렇게 생각할 수 있겠죠, 좋아요,
model, this encoder decoder.
우리는 이 확산 모델, 인코더-디코더를 다뤘는데,
How do we train an encoder decoder?
그럼 인코더-디코더는 어떻게 학습할까요?
Any ideas?
어떤 아이디어가 있나요?
Have we seen encoder decoders?
인코더 디코더에 대해 배운 적 있나요?
How about a variational autoencoder?
변분 오토인코더는요?
So in practice whenever you're training these latent diffusion
실제로 잠재 확산 모델을 훈련할
models, this encoder decoder tends
때 이 인코더 디코더는
to be a variational autoencoder, but we just
보통 변분 오토인코더인데, 변분
said there was a big problem with variational autoencoders
오토인코더의 큰 문제점은 출력이
is that they give you blurry outputs.
흐릿하다는 거죠.
And if this encoder decoder is going
만약 이 인코더 디코더가 흐릿한
to give you blurry outputs, the quality of the reconstructions
출력을 낸다면, 디코더에서 얻는 재구성
you get out of the decoder is going
품질이 후속
to bottleneck the quality of the generations you get out
확산 모델에서 생성되는 품질의
of the downstream diffusion model.
병목이 될 겁니다.
So if your encoder decoder is giving you
그래서 인코더 디코더가 흐릿하고 보기 안 좋은
blurry, ugly reconstructions, that's not going to fly.
재구성을 내면, 좋은 깨끗한 샘플을 얻을 수 없습니다.
That's not going to get us good clean samples.
그렇죠?
So anyone have an idea for cleaning up
그렇다면 VAE의 샘플
the sample quality of a VAE?
품질을 개선할 방법이 있을까요?
But something after the decoder in particular,
특히 디코더 이후에 뭔가를 추가해서
we can make it a GAN.
GAN으로 만들 수 있습니다.
So what we tend to do is actually
그래서 보통 이미지에서 잠재
train this encoder that encodes from an image
공간으로 인코딩하는 인코더, 잠재
into latent space, a decoder that goes from latent space
공간에서 이미지로 복원하는 디코더,
back to image, a discriminator that
가짜 이미지와 진짜
tries to tell the fake images from the real images,
이미지를 구분하는 판별기, 그리고
and then a diffusion model that generates
잠재 공간에서 생성하는 확산 모델을
these things in latent space.
함께 훈련합니다.
So this is basically why we have to walk through all
이런 다양한 생성 모델의 형태를
of these different formulations of generative models
모두 살펴보는 이유가 바로 현대의 파이프라인을
in order for you to understand the modern pipeline.
이해하기 위해서입니다.
Basically the state of the art in generative modeling
기본적으로 최신 생성 모델의 상태는
is is it a VAE?
VAE인가요?
Is it a GAN?
GAN인가요?
Is it a diffusion?
확산 모델인가요?
It's all of them.
모두 다입니다.
The modern generative modeling pipeline
현대 생성 모델 파이프라인은
involves training a VAE and a GAN and a diffusion model.
VAE, GAN, 확산 모델을 모두 훈련하는 것을 포함합니다.
I'm sorry.
죄송합니다.
It's a mess.
정말 엉망입니다.
OK, so then you might ask, what do the neural networks actually
좋습니다, 그렇다면 여러분은 신경망이 실제로 내부에서 어떻게
look like under the hood here?
생겼는지 궁금해할 수 있습니다.
So thankfully there is some sanity here
다행히도 지난 몇 년간 어느
the last couple of years.
정도 일관성이 있었습니다.
It turns out that relatively straightforward transformers
상대적으로 단순한 transformers가 이
actually can be applied to these diffusion models
diffusion 모델에 적용될 수 있고, 매우 잘
and they work really well.
작동한다는 것이 밝혀졌습니다.
These are typically called diffusion transformers or DiTs,
이것들은 보통 diffusion transformers 또는
but basically these are just standard diffusion models
DiTs라고 불리지만, 기본적으로는 특별한 기술이
or standard transformer blocks that really don't really have
거의 없는 표준 diffusion 모델이나 표준
much special sauce in them.
transformer 블록입니다.
There's a couple of questions.
몇 가지 질문이 있습니다.
The main question you need to solve in the architectural side
아키텍처 측면에서 해결해야 할 주요 질문은 어떻게
is how do you inject the conditioning information?
conditioning 정보를 주입하느냐입니다.
And in particular, the diffusion model
특히 diffusion 모델은
now needs to take three things as input.
이제 세 가지를 입력으로 받아야 합니다.
It needs to take your noisy image, it
노이즈가 있는 이미지, 타임스탬프
needs to take your timestamp t.
t를 받아야 합니다.
It also needs to take your conditioning signal,
또한 텍스트 같은
which it might be your text or something like that.
conditioning 신호도 받아야 합니다.
And then you have a couple different mechanisms
그리고 conditioning 신호를
for injecting that conditioning signal into your transformer
transformer 블록에 주입하는 몇 가지
blocks.
방법이 있습니다.
So the first is to predict a scale and shift that
첫 번째는 diffusion 블록의 중간
are going to be used to modulate some
활성화를 조절하는 데 사용할
of the intermediate activations of your diffusion block.
scale과 shift를 예측하는 것입니다.
And that's typically the way that we inject the timestamp
이것이 보통 diffusion 모델에
information into diffusion models.
타임스탬프 정보를 주입하는 방법입니다.
Another thing you can do is transformers
또 다른 방법은 transformers가
are just models of sequences so you can jam everything
시퀀스 모델이기 때문에 모든 것을
into the sequence.
시퀀스에 넣는 것입니다.
You can jam the timestamp
타임스탬프를 시퀀스에 넣을 수 있습니다.
You can jam your text into the sequence.
텍스트를 시퀀스에 넣을 수 있습니다.
You can jam whatever you want into the sequence
원하는 어떤 것도 시퀀스에 넣고
and have the transformer just model that sequence of data
transformer가 그 시퀀스 데이터를 함께 모델링하게
all together.
할 수 있습니다.
And you can do that either via cross-attention
이것은 cross-attention이나 joint
or joint attention and different models do both.
attention을 통해 할 수 있고, 다양한 모델이 둘 다 사용합니다.
And typically in modern diffusion
현대 diffusion DiTs에서는
DiTs we inject the timestamp through this scale shift
보통 타임스탬프를 scale shift 메커니즘으로
mechanism.
주입합니다.
And you inject the text or other conditioning signal
텍스트나 다른 conditioning 신호는 보통 시퀀스
through sequence concatenation usually cross-attention,
연결, 주로 cross-attention을 통해
but sometimes joint attention as well.
주입하지만 때로는 joint attention도 사용합니다.
So then how can you actually apply this
그렇다면 이것을 어떻게 다양한
to different problems?
문제에 적용할 수 있을까요?
So one task that people care about a lot
사람들이 많이 관심 갖는 작업 중
is the task of text to image generation.
하나는 텍스트에서 이미지 생성하는 작업입니다.
So here we're going to input a text prompt.
여기서는 텍스트 프롬프트를 입력할 것입니다.
This is one that I wrote yesterday.
이것은 제가 어제 쓴 프롬프트입니다.
A professional documentary photograph of a monkey
에펠탑 앞에서 호랑이와 악수하는
shaking hands with a tiger in front of the Eiffel Tower.
원숭이의 전문 다큐멘터리 사진입니다.
The monkey is wearing a hat made out of bananas.
원숭이는 바나나로 만든 모자를 쓰고 있습니다.
Tiger is standing on two legs and wearing a suit.
호랑이는 두 발로 서서 정장을 입고 있습니다.
And this is a real sample.
이것은 실제 샘플입니다.
It's crazy that this stuff works now,
이런 게 지금 작동한다니 정말
but I'm sure you've all seen these kind of things before.
놀랍지만, 여러분도 이런 것들을 본 적 있을 겁니다.
And the way that this works is you'll
작동하는 방식은 텍스트
take your text prompt, pass it through usually
프롬프트를 보통 사전 학습된 텍스트
a pre-trained text encoder.
인코더에 통과시키는 것입니다.
So actually I lied.
사실 제가 방금 거짓말을 했네요.
There's actually more models you have to train.
실제로 더 많은 모델을 학습해야 합니다.
In addition to an encoder and a decoder
인코더, 디코더, VAE,
and a VAE and a discriminator, you also
디스크리미네이터 외에도, 이 모든 것이
need to train a language model secretly
작동하게 하려면 비밀리에
to get these things to work.
언어 모델도 학습해야 합니다.
So you'll actually typically pick up a pre-trained text
그래서 보통은 사전 학습된 텍스트 인코더,
encoder, usually T5 clip, something
보통 T5나 CLIP 같은 걸
like that to give text embeddings.
가져와서 텍스트 임베딩을 얻습니다.
And usually the text encoder will be frozen.
그리고 보통 텍스트 인코더는 고정(frozen)됩니다.
Then those text embeddings you pass your text embeddings
그 다음 그 텍스트 임베딩과 노이즈가 있는 잠재
together with your noisy latents into your diffusion transformer
변수들을 함께 디퓨전 트랜스포머에 넣으면, 디퓨전
that also gets your diffusion time step that's
타임 스텝도 받아서 깨끗한
going to output clean latents.
잠재 변수를 출력합니다.
And this thing will go iteratively.
이 과정은 반복적으로 진행됩니다.
And that'll go through your VAE decoder
그리고 그 결과를 VAE 디코더에
to give you your final image.
통과시켜 최종 이미지를 얻습니다.
And just to put some numbers on this to make it concrete,
좀 더 구체적으로 숫자를 들어보면, 현재
one pretty powerful open source model right now
꽤 강력한 오픈소스 모델 중 하나가 FLUX1
is called FLUX1 dev.
dev라는 모델입니다.
They use the T5 and clip encoders.
이 모델은 T5와 CLIP 인코더를 사용합니다.
Their encoder uses 8x downsampling.
인코더는 8배 다운샘플링을 합니다.
They train a 12 billion parameter transformer
12억 파라미터의 트랜스포머
model on this and that transformer
모델을 학습하는데, 이 트랜스포머는
has an additional layer of downsampling on top of the VAE,
VAE 위에 추가 다운샘플링 레이어가 있어서
which is kind of messy.
좀 복잡합니다.
So it ends up having a sequence length of 1,024 image tokens.
그래서 최종적으로 1,024개의 이미지 토큰 시퀀스를 갖게 됩니다.
Another task that people care about a lot is text to video.
사람들이 많이 관심 가지는 또 다른 작업은 텍스트에서 비디오 생성입니다.
So we can input a text prompt and then
텍스트 프롬프트를 입력하면
output the pixels of a video that follow that text prompt.
그 텍스트에 맞는 비디오 픽셀을 출력하는 거죠.
And the pipeline basically looks the same.
파이프라인은 기본적으로 동일합니다.
So you're going to input a text through your pre-trained text
사전 학습된 텍스트 인코더에 텍스트를 입력하고
encoder, get noisy latents.
노이즈가 있는 잠재 변수를 얻습니다.
Importantly, the only difference is that your latents now
중요한 차이점은 잠재 변수에
have an extra dimension to accommodate the time.
시간 차원이 추가된다는 겁니다.
So in addition to two spatial dimensions hw,
즉, 공간적 차원 hw 외에 시간
you'll also have a time dimension in your latent
차원이 잠재 변수에 포함되어 깨끗한
and that will give you clean latents.
잠재 변수를 얻습니다.
And then your decoder, this is typically
그리고 디코더는 보통
going to be a spatial temporal autoencoder now.
시공간 오토인코더가 됩니다.
So it will downsample both spatially and temporally.
그래서 공간적, 시간적으로 다운샘플링을 합니다.
So then it will take your latents
그 후 잠재 변수를
and then upsample them into pixels,
픽셀로 업샘플링해서
which will give you a video.
비디오를 생성합니다.
And this is actually a generated video from Meta's GOOVIGEN paper
이것은 작년에 나온 Meta의 GOOVIGEN 논문에서
that came out last year.
생성한 실제 비디오입니다.
And that's putting some particular numbers
여기에 구체적인 숫자도 나와
on this thing.
있습니다.
And the key takeaway of these video generation models
이 비디오 생성
is that they get very expensive to train due to the sequence
모델들의 핵심은 시퀀스
length, because if you want to generate
길이 때문에
high FPS, high resolution, high frame rate video,
학습 비용이 매우 높다는
it just ends up with a lot of tokens.
점입니다.
So we said that with a fairly state of the art text to image
고해상도, 고프레임 비디오를 생성하려면
diffusion model, that transformer ended up working
토큰 수가
on a sequence of 1,024 image tokens.
엄청나게 많아지기 때문입니다.
For this text to video diffusion model,
앞서 말한 최첨단 텍스트-이미지
even though the overall architecture
디퓨전 모델은
looks pretty similar, the biggest difference
1,024개의 이미지
is in the sequence length.
토큰 시퀀스를 처리했습니다.
Now they actually need to process 76,000 video tokens
텍스트-비디오 디퓨전 모델은 전체 구조는 비슷하지만
to process this, to create this high resolution video with a lot
시퀀스 길이가 가장 큰
of frames.
차이점입니다.
So that's where the expense happens
이 모델은 고해상도, 다수의
in these video diffusion models is actually processing
프레임을 가진 비디오를 생성하기 위해
these really long sequences.
76,000개의 비디오 토큰을 처리해야 합니다.
So I think basically the last year
그래서 이 비디오 디퓨전 모델들의 비용이 많이
has pretty much been the era of video diffusion models.
드는 이유는 바로 이렇게 긴 시퀀스를 처리하기 때문입니다.
So it basically seems like every week almost for the past year,
지난 1년은 사실상 비디오 디퓨전 모델의
there's been a new interesting video diffusion
시대였다고 할
model coming out.
수 있습니다.
And these have been a mix of open source models, models
거의 매주 새로운 흥미로운 비디오 디퓨전
that have technical reports.
모델이 발표되고 있습니다.
So they give you some details about the model architecture
이 모델들은 오픈소스 모델, 기술
and the training and purely industrial models
보고서가 있는 모델, 그리고 아무 정보도
where they don't tell you anything,
공개하지 않고 신용카드
but they'll take your credit card number
결제만 받는
and let you generate samples from it.
산업용 모델들이 혼합되어 있습니다.
So I'm not going to go through all of these one by one,
그래서 이 모든 것을 하나하나 다 설명하지는 않겠지만,
but I just wanted to give the sense
지난 18개월 동안
of this has been a really hot topic really the past 18 months.
이 주제가 정말 뜨거운 관심사였다는 점을 말씀드리고 싶었습니다.
And in particular there was this really influential
특히 2024년 3월에 OpenAI에서 나온
blog post from OpenAI called Sora that came out
Sora라는 매우 영향력 있는 블로그 글이
in March 2024, which was not the first diffusion model on videos,
있었는데, 비디오에 대한 첫 번째 diffusion 모델은 아니었지만
but it was the first one that gave really, really, really good
정말, 정말, 정말 좋은 결과를 낸 첫
results.
번째 모델이었습니다.
And they adopted this modern diffusion transformer
그들은 최신 diffusion transformer와 rectified
plus rectified flow.
flow를 도입했습니다.
Actually, I don't know if they were
사실 Sora에서 rectified flow를
using rectified flow in Sora.
사용했는지는 잘 모르겠습니다.
I don't know if they said, but they were one of the first
그들이 말했는지 모르겠지만, 이 diffusion
to really scale up these diffusion transformers
transformer를 대규모로 확장해서 정말 잘 작동하게
and get this thing to work really well.
만든 최초의 팀 중 하나였습니다.
And then that was the four minute mile moment
그리고 그게 비디오 diffusion 모델에서 4분의 1마일
in video diffusion models.
돌파 순간과 같았습니다.
And then all the other big companies took notice of that
그 후 다른 큰 회사들도 이를 주목하고 빠르게
and quickly tried to replicate Sora.
Sora를 복제하려고 했습니다.
So I said it's felt like for the past year and a half
그래서 지난 1년 반 동안 거의 매주 새로운
that almost every week, there's been
최첨단 비디오 diffusion
a brand new, state of the art video diffusion model.
모델이 나오는 것 같은 느낌이 들었습니다.
And today is no exception because an hour and a half--
오늘도 예외는 아니어서, 오늘 오전
at 11:00 AM this morning, Google announced Veo 3,
11시에 구글이 Veo 3를 발표했는데, 지금 당장 가장
which is almost certainly the best generative model of video
뛰어난 비디오 생성 모델일
out there right now.
가능성이 큽니다.
I literally read the blog post while I
저는 여기 오는 길 차 안에서
was in the car on the way here, but it seems cool.
블로그 글을 읽었는데, 정말 멋져 보입니다.
Here's some samples from V3.
여기 V3의 샘플 몇 개입니다.
So these are actually generated videos
이것들은 실제로 구글의 새 모델로 텍스트
from a text prompt in Google's new model, kind of crazy.
프롬프트에서 생성된 비디오입니다, 꽤 놀랍죠.
Also this model also models sound jointly
또한 이 모델은 소리도 함께 모델링해서
so they can output audio along with the video frames.
비디오 프레임과 함께 오디오도 출력할 수 있습니다.
This is another generated one, so you
이것도 또 다른 생성된 예시인데,
can tell what you want to happen in text.
텍스트로 원하는 내용을 말하면,
It'll fly over here and looks crazy.
여기 위로 날아가고 정말 멋져 보입니다.
OK, so I thought that's just fun to incorporate new stuff.
네, 새로운 것을 접목하는 게 재미있을 것 같아서 말씀드렸습니다.
OK, so one big problem with diffusion
좋습니다, diffusion의 큰 문제 중
is that during sampling it's really slow.
하나는 샘플링할 때 정말 느리다는 점입니다.
We said that sampling was this iterative procedure.
우리는 샘플링이 반복적인 절차라고 말했죠.
And these models can be really big.
그리고 이 모델들은 정말 클 수 있습니다.
These can be models with tens of billions
이 모델들은 수십억 개의
of parameters potentially operating on sequence lengths
파라미터를 가진 모델일 수 있고, 수만 개
of tens of thousands or more.
이상의 시퀀스 길이에서 작동할 수 있습니다.
So these things get really slow at inference time
그래서 이런 것들은 추론 시에 정말
because even with rectified flow,
느려집니다. rectified
you need like tens of iterations of the model at inference time.
flow를 사용해도 추론 시에 수십 번의 반복이 필요하기 때문입니다.
So the solution is a category of algorithms
그래서 해결책은 distillation이라고 불리는
called distillation, which we don't have time to get into.
알고리즘 범주인데, 시간 관계상 자세히 다루지는 않겠습니다.
I just wanted to put a couple of references here,
여기 몇 가지 참고문헌을 넣어서 이런
make you aware that this exists as a set of techniques.
기술들이 존재한다는 것을 알려드리고 싶었습니다.
So distillation algorithms are basically
distillation 알고리즘은
ways that you can take a diffusion model that normally
기본적으로 diffusion 모델이 추론
would take 30, 50, 100 iterations at inference time
시 30, 50, 100번의 반복을 거쳐야 좋은
to get good samples and then modify the model in some way
샘플을 얻을 수 있는데, 모델을 어떤 식으로든 수정해서
such that you can take many, many fewer steps on inference
추론 시 훨씬 적은 단계로도 좋은 샘플을 얻을
and still get good samples.
수 있게 하는 방법입니다.
They tend to sacrifice sample quality.
이들은 보통 샘플 품질을 어느 정도 희생합니다.
So the whole trick in distillation methods
그래서 distillation
is trying to maintain the sample quality as good as you
방법의 핵심은 추론 시 적은 단계로
can, while still letting you take fewer
샘플링하면서도 샘플 품질을 최대한
samples at inference time.
유지하는 것입니다.
And some distillation methods let you get all the way
어떤 distillation
down to single step sampling, which is really cool,
방법은 단일 단계 샘플링까지
although they tend to take quite a hit on the generation quality
가능하게 하는데, 정말 멋지지만 그럴 때는
when you do that.
생성 품질이 꽤 떨어지는 경향이 있습니다.
I'm not going to go through these,
이것들을 자세히 다루지는
but I just put some references here
않겠지만, distillation
to different papers on distillation
관련 여러 논문들을
if you want to take a look.
참고문헌으로 넣어두었습니다.
And this is a really active and evolving area of research.
이 분야는 매우 활발하고 계속 발전하는 연구 영역입니다.
So if you look at these references,
이 참고문헌들을 보면
these are from 2024, from 2025.
2024년, 2025년 논문들이 포함되어 있습니다.
So these are stuff that people are working on right
즉, 사람들이 지금도 더 나은
now is how do we get better distillation,
distillation 방법과
how do we get diffusion models to be more
diffusion 모델의 추론 효율성을 높이는
efficient at inference time?
방법을 연구하고 있다는 뜻입니다.
So another thing.
또 다른 점은요.
So I mentioned that diffusion has this black hole of math
그래서 diffusion에는 수학의 블랙홀 같은 게 있어서 빠져들 수
that you can get sucked into.
있다고 말씀드렸습니다.
And we intentionally sidestepped that
그리고 우리는 의도적으로
by just walking very intuitively through rectified flow models,
그 부분을 피해서 rectified flow 모델을
giving you a geometric intuition for the problem
직관적으로 설명하며, 수학적으로
without really diving through any math that proves anything.
증명하는 대신 문제에 대한 기하학적 직관을 드렸습니다.
So I wanted to give you just a brief sense of what
그래서 이런 형식들에 대해 간단히
some of these formalisms are, but we're not
소개해 드리려 하지만,
going to be able to go through them in detail.
자세히 다루지는 않을 겁니다.
So here's restating the rectified flow objective.
자, rectified flow 목표를 다시 말씀드리겠습니다.
We said that during training we're
훈련 중에는 데이터
going to sample our x's and our z's according
분포에 따른 x와 노이즈 분포에
to our data distribution and our noise distribution.
따른 z를 샘플링한다고 했습니다.
We're going two sample t according to some distribution
그리고 t는 우리가 선택한 분포 pt에서
pt that we choose either on uniform, logit-normal
샘플링하는데, 보통 uniform, logit-normal,
or shifted, something like that.
shifted 같은 분포입니다.
And then we'll set xt equal to the linear interpolation
그다음 xt는 x와 z 사이의 선형
between x and z.
보간으로 설정합니다.
We'll set our-- now we've written this a little bit
이 슬라이드에서는 조금 다르게
differently in this slide.
표현했습니다.
Now we're writing down a ground truth velocity vgt
지금은 네트워크가 예측해야 하는 실제
that we want the network to predict which is z minus x.
속도 vgt를 z 빼기 x로 정의했습니다.
We compute a predicted v from the network
네트워크에 노이즈가 섞인
by passing our noisy xt and our t,
xt와 t를 넣어 예측된
then compute an L2 loss, minimizing
v를 계산하고, vgt와 예측된
the vgt and the predicted v from the network.
v 사이의 L2 손실을 최소화합니다.
When I said that there's a lot of different formalisms,
다양한 형식과 종류의 diffusion이
a lot of different flavors of diffusion, what a lot of these
있다고 했는데, 이들은
look to is different functional hyperparameters
일반적으로 이 기본 설정에서 함수형 하이퍼파라미터를 다르게
in this general setup.
설정하는 겁니다.
So in more generalized flavors of diffusion usually
좀 더 일반화된 diffusion에서는 보통
you might vary what is this pt distribution.
pt 분포를 바꾸기도 합니다.
Usually you don't vary the noise distribution.
노이즈 분포는 보통 바꾸지 않는데, 연속 모델에서는 거의 항상 Gaussian입니다.
This is almost always Gaussian, at least for continuous models,
하지만 noisy xt를 어떻게
but what you will vary is how do you compute that noisy xt.
계산하느냐를 바꾸는데,
And in general that will be some functional combination-- that
일반적으로 noisy xt는
will be some linear combination of x and z.
x와 z의 선형 조합이며,
And the linear combination weights will in general
이 선형 조합의 가중치는 보통 t의 함수로
be some function of t, but what exactly that function is
표현되지만, 정확한 함수는 diffusion
depends on the diffusion formulation.
공식에 따라 다릅니다.
Then what also varies is what is that ground truth target that we
그럼 모델에게 예측하라고 하는 그 실제 정답
ask the model to predict.
타깃도 달라집니다.
It's always going to be some linear combination of our data
항상 데이터 샘플 x와
sample x and our latent z.
잠재 변수 z의 선형 결합일 겁니다.
And again, what are the linear combination
그리고 다시 말하지만, 선형 결합
weights might be functions of t in some formulations.
가중치는 어떤 공식에서는 t의 함수일 수 있습니다.
So basically and then we're going
기본적으로 우리는 모델에게
to ask the model to-- we're going
노이즈가 섞인
to give it that noisy xt and the t, get a predicted y.
xt와 t를 주고, y를 예측하게 할 겁니다.
And then always compute an L2 loss between the two.
그리고 항상 두 값 사이의 L2 손실을 계산합니다.
I mean, not always, but usually.
항상은 아니지만 보통 그렇습니다.
And then what varies is basically
그리고 달라지는 것은 기본적으로
what are these different functional forms.
이 함수들의 다양한 형태입니다.
What are these different functions
이 함수들이
that we plot, that we slot into these four
네 군데 다른 위치에
different spots in this thing?
들어가는 함수들인 거죠.
So in the case of rectified flow it's fairly simple.
rectified flow의 경우는 꽤 간단합니다.
These all take these really simple forms.
모두 아주 단순한 형태를 가집니다.
And ct and dt are actually just constants.
그리고 ct와 dt는 사실 상수입니다.
There's another flavor of this called variance preserving where
variance preserving이라는 다른 방식도 있는데, 여기서는 이
you collapse these two into one scalar hyperparameter called
둘을 sigma(t)라는 하나의 스칼라
sigma of t.
하이퍼파라미터로 합칩니다.
And now you have these linear combinations
이제 이런 특정한 방식으로 선형
in this particular way.
결합을 하게 됩니다.
And you choose this because if x and z are independent and have
x와 z가 독립이고 단위 분산을 가진다면, 출력도
unit variance, then your output also
단위 분산을 가지도록 보장하기 때문에
is guaranteed to have unit variance.
이렇게 선택하는 겁니다.
So that collapses these two functional hyperparameters
그래서 이 두 함수형 하이퍼파라미터를
into just one noise schedule and then
하나의 노이즈 스케줄로
you still need to choose that somehow.
합치고, 그걸 어떻게든 선택해야 합니다.
In combination with variance preserving,
variance preserving과
there's also variance exploding is
함께 variance exploding이라는
another one where you'll set at equals 1, bt equal to again
다른 방식도 있는데, 여기서는 at를 1로, bt를 다시
some sigma of t.
sigma(t)로 설정합니다.
And then you need to choose that somehow.
그리고 나서 어떻게든 그것을 선택해야 합니다.
There's a lot of different targets that people will choose.
사람들이 선택하는 목표가 정말 다양합니다.
Sometimes they'll ask the network
때로는 네트워크에게 깨끗한
to predict the clean data.
데이터를 예측하라고 합니다.
Sometimes they'll ask the model to predict
때로는 모델에게 추가된 노이즈를
the noise that was added.
예측하라고 하기도 합니다.
Sometimes they'll ask the network
때로는 두 가지의
to predict some linear combination of the two.
선형 결합을 예측하라고 하기도 합니다.
And in the case of rectified flow,
rectified flow의
you are just predicting that velocity vector that
경우에는 데이터에서 노이즈로 직접 향하는
points from a data directly to a noise,
속도 벡터를 예측하는 것이지만,
but in more in different flavors of diffusion, all of these
다른 다양한 diffusion 방식에서는 이 모든
can change.
것이 달라질 수 있습니다.
Then you might be wondering choosing
하이퍼파라미터를 선택하는 것만 해도 충분히 어렵다고
hyperparameters is bad enough.
생각할 수 있겠죠.
Now we need to choose hyperparameters, which
이제는 t의 함수인 하이퍼파라미터도
are themselves functions of t.
선택해야 합니다.
This is crazy.
이건 정말 미친 짓입니다.
You're never going to set these intuitively,
직관적으로 설정할 수 없으니
so you have to be guided by some kind of math.
어떤 수학적 가이드가 필요합니다.
And there's basically three different mathematical
diffusion 모델을 훈련할 때
formalisms that people think about when
사람들이 생각하는 수학적 형식이 기본적으로
training diffusion models that again, we will not walk through
세 가지가 있는데, 실제로 다루지는
in practice.
않겠습니다.
I just want to get you to know the existence of.
그저 존재한다는 것만 알아두시길 바랍니다.
The first is that diffusion is a latent variable model.
첫 번째는 diffusion이 잠재 변수 모델이라는 점입니다.
We have our clean data samples x0,
깨끗한 데이터 샘플 x0가
but then associated to every clean data
있지만, 각 깨끗한
sample there exists some sequence
샘플에 대응하는
of corrupted or noisy samples that correspond
일련의 손상되거나 노이즈가 섞인 샘플들이
to that clean sample.
존재합니다.
And we can't observe them.
우리는 그것들을 관찰할 수 없습니다.
We don't know what they are, but we need
무엇인지 모르지만 어떻게든
to figure them out somehow.
알아내야 합니다.
So that's a latent variable model.
이것이 잠재 변수 모델입니다.
That ends up looking a lot like a variational autoencoder.
이것은 변분 오토인코더와 매우 비슷하게 보입니다.
Remember, in a variational autoencoder we had a z and an x.
기억하시죠, 변분 오토인코더에서는 z와 x가 있었고, z는 관찰하지 못했습니다.
We didn't observe the z.
어떻게든 이 모델을 훈련시키고 싶었죠.
We wanted to train this thing somehow.
그리고 변분 오토인코더에서 사용한 것과 매우 유사한 수학적 기법을 사용해 데이터의 우도에 대한 변분 하한을 최대화할 수 있습니다.
Then it turns out you can use a very similar mathematical trick
이것이 diffusion의
as we did in variational autoencoders
잠재 변수
and maximize some variational lower bound
모델 해석을
of the likelihood of the data.
낳습니다.
And that gives rise to this latent variable model
diffusion에 대한 완전히 다른
interpretation of diffusion.
해석은 score function을 모델링한다는 것입니다.
A totally different interpretation of diffusion
x의 분포 pdata가 주어지면, score function이라는
is that it models something called the score function.
멋진 개념이 있는데, 이는 pdata(x)의 로그에 대해 x로 미분한 것입니다.
So given a distribution pdata of x,
직관적으로 분포가 주어지면, score
there's this nice thing called the score function
function은 높은 확률
of the distribution, which is the derivative with respect
밀도 영역을 가리키는
to x of the log of pdata of x.
벡터 필드입니다.
And intuitively given a distribution,
데이터 공간의 어떤 점에서든
the score function is a vector field
score function은
that points towards areas of high probability density.
높은 데이터 밀도 영역을 향하는 벡터가 됩니다.
So for any point in the data space,
또 다른 diffusion 해석은 diffusion이 데이터 분포의
the score function is going to be
score function을 학습한다는
a vector that points you towards areas of high data density.
것입니다. 사실, 데이터 분포에 노이즈가 섞인 다양한 수준에 대응하는 score function 집합을 학습합니다.
And now another interpretation of diffusion
즉, diffusion은 점점 더 많은
is that diffusion is learning the score function of the data
알려진 노이즈로 진짜 데이터 분포를
distribution and in fact, learning
손상시키는 노이즈 분포 계열에
a set of score functions corresponding
대응하는 score function
to different levels of noise on the data distribution.
계열을 학습하려는 시도라는 또 다른 해석이 있습니다.
So there's another interpretation
이것은
of diffusion, which is that it's trying
완전히 다른
to learn a family of score functions corresponding
수학적 형식이지만
to a family of noise distributions
결국 매우 비슷한
that corrupt the true data distribution with increasing
알고리즘으로
amounts of known noise.
이어집니다.
And that's a totally different mathematical formalism
그리고 최근에 등장한 세 번째 해석은
that gives rise to very similar looking algorithm at the end.
diffusion을 확률 미분 방정식을 푸는 것으로 보는 것입니다.
And then the third one that's come onto the scene a little bit
솔직히 저도 이 부분은 완전히
more recently is this notion of diffusion
이해하지 못해서 질문은
as solving stochastic differential equations.
너무 많이 하지 마세요.
And I got to admit I don't fully understand this one myself, so
하지만 아이디어는
don't ask me too many questions, but the idea
노이즈 분포에서
is that you want to write down some differential
데이터 분포로 샘플을
equation that's going to write down some infinitesimal way
미세하게 이동시키는
to transport samples from a noise distribution
미분 방정식을 작성하는
into samples from a data distribution.
것입니다.
And then inference, then the neural network
그리고 추론 단계에서,
is basically learning some kind of numeric integrator,
신경망은 기본적으로 우리가 쓸 수 있는 확률 미분
some numeric integrator to this stochastic differential equation
방정식에 대한 어떤 수치적 적분기를
that we can write down.
배우는 겁니다.
And this opens up a whole new way of thinking about it because
이것은 확률 미분 방정식
from under the lens of stochastic differential
관점에서 보면 추론 시점에
equations, then we get access to two whole different categories
샘플링할 수 있는 완전히 다른 두 가지 방법 범주에
of methods to sample from these things at inference time.
접근할 수 있게 해줍니다.
And from this perspective, the naive gradient descent type
이 관점에서 보면, rectified flow에서 본
approach that we saw in rectified flow
단순한 경사 하강법 방식은
basically corresponds to a forward Euler type of integrator
확률 미분 방정식 위에서의 전진
on top of a stochastic differential equation.
오일러 적분기와 대응됩니다.
And then under this interpretation,
이 해석 아래에서는 점수
you can imagine doing all kinds of more complicated integrators
함수(score function)를 따라 더 잘 나아가기
to maybe do a better job at marching along this score
위해 훨씬 복잡한 적분기를 사용할 수도 있다고 상상할
function.
수 있습니다.
So again, these are deep waters.
다시 말하지만, 이건 깊은 내용입니다.
There's papers that go into great detail on all
이 모든 것에 대해 자세히 다룬
these things.
논문들이 있습니다.
And a blog post that I really like
제가 정말 좋아하는 블로그 글 중
is this one by Sander Dielman on perspectives on diffusion,
하나는 Sander Dielman이 쓴 'perspectives
who actually gave eight different perspectives
on diffusion'이라는 글로, 확산
on different ways to think about or view diffusion models.
모델을 생각하거나 보는 여덟 가지 다른 관점을 제시합니다.
So this is an excellent post.
정말 훌륭한 글입니다.
I would highly recommend.
강력히 추천합니다.
I would actually highly recommend
사실 그가 확산 모델에
everything he's written about diffusion models.
대해 쓴 모든 글을 강력히 추천합니다.
All his blog posts are amazing.
그의 모든 블로그 글이 훌륭합니다.
Autoregressive models actually come back.
오토리그레시브 모델도 다시 등장합니다.
We can do the same thing, encoder-decoder
같은 방식으로 인코더-디코더에 오토리그레시브
and put an autoregressive model on there too.
모델을 붙일 수 있습니다.
So just sneaking this in there at the end,
마지막에 살짝 덧붙이자면, 확산 모델 외에 현대
in addition to diffusion models, the other modern recipe
생성 모델링의 또 다른 방법은 이산 변분
for generative modeling is to train an autoregressive model
오토인코더로 계산된 이산 잠재
on discrete latents that are computed
변수에 대해 오토리그레시브
by a discrete variational autoencoder.
모델을 훈련하는 것입니다.
So that's why we did for generative models that we did,
그래서 우리가 생성 모델로 다룬 GAN, VAE,
GANs, VAEs, autoregressive models diffusion
오토리그레시브 모델, 확산
because it turns out they all get used in modern machine
모델 모두가 현대 머신러닝 파이프라인에서
learning pipelines.
실제로 사용됩니다.
So that's basically the summary of today.
이게 오늘 내용의 요약입니다.
Today we did a whirlwind tour of two different categories
오늘은 두 가지 생성 모델 범주를 빠르게
of generative models.
훑어봤습니다.
We talked about generative adversarial networks as well as
생성적 적대 신경망과 확산 모델에 대해
diffusion models.
이야기했습니다.
And we saw their modern full pipeline instantiated
그리고 이들을 잠재 확산 모델에서 현대적인 전체 파이프라인으로
in latent diffusion models, which is of a nice way
구현한 것을 봤습니다. 이게 생성
to wrap up this generative modeling section,
모델링 섹션을 잘 마무리하는 방법입니다.
because all the generative models that we saw basically
왜냐하면 우리가 본 모든 생성 모델이
come back and come together to form these big modern pipelines.
결국 다시 모여서 큰 현대 파이프라인을 형성하기 때문입니다.
So thanks and next time, we'll talk about vision and language.
감사합니다. 다음 시간에는 비전과 언어에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.